<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the end of the world and iudgement of our Lord Iesus Christe to come, and of the moste perillous dangers of this our moste corrupt age, and by what meanes the godly may auoid the harmes thereof, sermons preached in latin in the assembly of the clergie by Henry Bullinger, and now lately englished by Thomas Potter</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845179</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845179</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17215)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 184:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the end of the world and iudgement of our Lord Iesus Christe to come, and of the moste perillous dangers of this our moste corrupt age, and by what meanes the godly may auoid the harmes thereof, sermons preached in latin in the assembly of the clergie by Henry Bullinger, and now lately englished by Thomas Potter</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Potter, Thomas, fl. 1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By John Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint in part from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint in part from STC because title page as filmed too dark to read.</note>
                  <note>There are two editions of this work; one without a comma after "world " in the title and C2v catchword "moreouer", the other with a comma after "world" in the title and C2v catchword "more"--STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition there is no comma after "world" in the title and C2v catchword is "moreouer".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page defective.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Boston Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgement Day --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10066:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Of the end of the world and iudgement of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte to come, and <hi>of the moſte perillous dangers of</hi> this our moſte corrupt age, and by what meanes the godly may auoid the harmes therof / two ſermons preached in latin in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the clergie by Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Bullinger / and now ſorely engliſhed by Thomas Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>¶Heerin are expounded the <hi>words of our ſauiour. Mat. 24.</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the end of the world, &amp; the laſt iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Alſo the words of Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elin the <hi>7.</hi> chap. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the moſt troubleſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the Pope / &amp; the end therof. Finally the woords of the Apoſtle. <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>5.</hi> concerning the perils of the laſt times / and the excellency and fulnes of holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London at <hi>the long shop in the Pultrie</hi>
               </hi> by Iohn Allde.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10066:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10066:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the end of the world &amp; the</hi> Iudgement of our Lord Ieſus <hi>Chriſte to come, and of the moſte</hi> gréeuous perils of this our moſte corrupt age or time.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The firſt Sermon of Henry <hi>Bullinger.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE matter it</hi> ſelf requireth, and the examples bothe of the Prophets and alſo of the Apoſtles doo inſtruct vs, that all our Eccleſiaſticall preachings (doctrines I mean, admonitions, rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, exhortations, counſails and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortings) are to be framed according to the time. And moreouer, that all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall dooings are to be referred vnto edifying.</p>
               <p>But if wée ſhould now intreat and ſpeak as the preſent time requireth, and to the prophet of vs all, who are moſte of vs miniſters of the Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are wee moſte cheefely aſſembled héere to th'entent ſomewhat ſhould bée ſaid concerning the duety of our office, that is moſte principally requiſit to knowe: there appéereth to vs no matter
<pb facs="tcp:10066:3"/>
more profitable, nor more neceſſary, then to admoniſh your holineſſe (ye Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and brethern honorable and moſt déerly beloued) of the conſummation of the world,<note place="margin">The prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> and the finall iudgement of Chriſte Ieſus our Lord. And alſo as our ſpeciall duty requireth) diligently and erneſtly to ſtir vp the people of Chriſte, committed to our charge: vnto a ſober watchfulnes, leſt ſudainly and vnwares the day of the Lord ſteale vppon them, which vndoutedly cannot be far of, and which our elders afore vs, teachers in the Church abooue a thouſand or ix. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yéeres paſt, did think to be at hand.</p>
               <p>How much rather ought we (vppon whom the ends of the world are come, &amp; who alſo haue moſt manifeſtly ſéenful filled very many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Propheſies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue been ſet foorth concerning the end of the world, and the things that ſhould come to paſſe (immediatly before the day of Iudgement) to lift vp our heds, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that our redemption euen now dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth néer.</p>
               <p>Chriſte Ieſus our Lord béeing yet a fauourable high Préeſt of the faithful, on, the right hand of his father, but héeraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the laſt, a moſte ſeuere and yet
<pb facs="tcp:10066:3"/>
moſte iuſt iudge of all the whole world, graunt mée habilitie to ſpeak duly vnto you, and you grace plentifully to heare with frute to the glory of his name and edifying of his Church. And becauſe ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed <hi>Peeter</hi> the Apoſtle, the cheef teacher of this Church, and moſte faithful Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Ieſus Chriſte our Lord (ſaith). <hi>If any man ſpeak: let him ſpeak as the ſayings of God.</hi> I wil ſtudiouſly inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to ſhewe foorth, and with as much plainnes as I may<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to open my whole matter euen with the woords of Chriſte our Lord, and with the ſayings of the Prophets and Apoſtles. For the holy Prophets in whom was the Spirite of Chriſte. <hi>Daniel</hi> moſte chéefely and <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> (omitting <hi>Eſay</hi> &amp; <hi>Ezechiel</hi>) haue moſt diligently and copiouſly inſtructed the Church of God with their propheſies concerning the latter times of the world and the iudgement of Chriſte our Lord to come.</p>
               <p>But Chriſte our Lord, the light and fulfilling of the lawe and the Prophets, hath ſo largely and ſo manifeſtly deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of theſe matters, that if any man doo yet deſire a more plain expoſition: may ſéem to ſéek at the Sun béeing of it ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:10066:4"/>
moſte bright ſhining, a light much brigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ꝓphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt touching the end of the world and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the laſt dayes.</note>He béeing demaunded of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Oliuet,</hi> and in the ſight of the moſt famoꝰ Citie of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> what ſhould be the token of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, and of the end of the world: Made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. <hi>That the holy Citie of Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem should firſt of all be taken and laid flat to the ground, and that the Iewes them ſelues should be led captiue into all nations.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wath. 24</note> 
                  <hi>And that the Goſpel of the kingdome should be receiued of all na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s throughout the whole world. And that afterward should falſe Prophets go abrode, who with falſe doctrine and faied miracles should deceiue the world &amp; that vvith ſuch prohability &amp; happy ſucceſſe: that euen the very elect should haue combrance thervvith.</hi> Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things he reſiteth, <hi>Falſe teachers and falſe Chriſtes, and euen thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtes alſo,</hi> that ſhould forſake the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry true Chriſte the ſonne of the eternall God, and ſhould not ſincerely vnto the faithful ſhew him foorth, ſitting on the right hand of his father: but in the earth, <hi>in the deſert, in ſundry and diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and alſo euen En tois temeios</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:10066:4"/>
is to ſay, <hi>in cloſe and ſecret places, in Cheſts and Ambries.</hi> For the <hi>Grecians</hi> call <hi>Temeia</hi> ſecret and wel fenced pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where treaſures are laid vp, alſo the hidden and priuy places of a houſe, and the very Ambry or Spence. And the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sacrament houſes diligently fenced with Locks and boltes, the Popes men call them Ambries,<note place="margin">As ſure as God is in the Ambry</note> out of the which as out of an Ambry, they bring foorth <hi>Via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum,</hi> their viage, prouiſion or Howzel (as they call it.</p>
               <p>But our Lord in the Goſpel with loud voice crieth out, ſaying. <hi>Do not beleeue them, doo not go foorth, doo not be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeue them. Beeholde, I haue tolde you before.</hi> And héeer he addeth by and by, <hi>that greeuous perſecutions shall ariſe againſt the godly,</hi> He ſaith, <hi>that there shalbe great troubles, that there shall appeer tokens in the Sun, in the moon and in the ſtarres, that ſome shalbe gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vvith great pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciuenes through des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, &amp; that ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e beeing diſſolute &amp; vva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton through to much &amp; a certain care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecuritie, shall be in that laſt day o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uervvhelmed, &amp; that the vvorld shalbe about the end altogither ſuch as it vvas before the flud &amp; in the daies of Loth,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:5"/>
vvhile the Giants &amp; Sodomites lay ſlee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping and ſnorting quietly in the dung of vvickedneſſe,</hi> deſpiſing all the good ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monitions of God, giuen vnto them by the holy Fathers, in ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came vpon them vnlooked for. <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle of Chriſte, ſpeaking alſo of that vngodly ſecuritie.<note place="margin">2. Theſſe. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Of the times</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>&amp; at vvhat mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our Lord vvil come to execute iudgement: there is no need for mee to vvrite vnto you brethern. For you your ſelues do plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knovve that the day of the Lord vvil come as a theef in the night. For vvhen they shall ſay peace and quiet ſafetie: then ſuddain deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> shall come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the pain of childe bearing vp on a vvoman in trauail, and they shall not eſcape.</hi> But our Lord in his Goſpel procedeth with his Prophetical expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note> &amp; ſaith moreouer. <hi>Iniquitie shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound and the loue of many shall wax colde, ſo that the ſonne of man vvhen he commeth: shall ſcarcely finde faith vpon the earth.</hi> Saint <hi>Peeter</hi> alſo fortel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of the extreme wickednes of this laſt age.<note place="margin">2. Peeter. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſtir vp your mindes</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the vvords that haue beene ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heertofore by the holy Prophets
<pb facs="tcp:10066:5"/>
and alſo the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of vs the Apoſtles of our Lord and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auiour. This vnderſtand ye firſt, that in the laſt daies shall come mockers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvhich vvil vvalke after their ovvne luſt, and ſay. VVhere is the promiſe of his comming? For, ſins our fathers died, all things conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevv in the ſame eſtate from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning as they vvere firſt made.</hi> Our Lord alſo in the goſpel addeth moreouer to all theſe things <hi>That hee vvil come in his glory ſudainly and vnloked for, to iudge the quick &amp; the dead, &amp; that hee vvil giue revvards of life to the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, &amp; vvil commit the vvicked to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Hel fire. For as the lightning</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forth of the eaſt, and shineth euen vnto the vveſt: ſo shalbe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the ſonne of man. Take heed therfor vnto your ſelues leſt your harts bee oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkennes, and with the cares of this life, and ſo that day ſteale ſudainly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you. For truely it shall come vpon all the inhabitants of the earth like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſnare. VVatch therfore praying at all times, that ye may be counted vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eſcape all theſe things that are to come, and to ſtand before the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:10066:6"/>
man.</hi> Verily in this place our Lord is earneſt &amp; vrgeth ſo, as in no other place more vehemently, exhorting all people of all kindes, and of all ages vnto a ſober watchfulnes. In Saint <hi>Mark. VVatch</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for ye knovve not when your Lord vvil come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>vvhether in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or at midnighr, whether at the cock crowing or in the dawning, leſt if he come ſudainly, he finde you ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</hi> In S, <hi>Mathew</hi> hée ſetteth foorth very many parables, ſo the intent hee might the more déeply faſten this thing in the mindes of all men. For he ſetteth before vs <hi>An houſeholder that vvatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> leſt the théef in the night breaking in to his houſe ſhould ſteale away all his ſubſtance. He ſetteth foorth <hi>A faithfull and wiſe ſeruaunt,</hi> that miniſtreth meat in due time to the whole houſholde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge. On the other ſide, he ſetteth againſt him a <hi>noughty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,</hi> vnthriftliy waſting his maiſters goods, and alſo very vniuſtly dealing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his felowe ſeruants, moreouer drunken and vnwatchful, not any whit regarding his maiſters comming: whom taken with the fault he dooth rent in pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like a Traitor. He ſetteth before vs
<pb facs="tcp:10066:6"/>
                  <hi>Ten Virgins,</hi> wherof fiue were ſober and wiſe, but th'other v. were fooliſh and ſlouthful, and therfore ſhut out of the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the wedding.</p>
               <p>Furthermore hée ſetteth before vs a certain <hi>Noble houſe holder,</hi> that looke his iourney into a far countrey, and yet firſt before his departure diſtributed his goods by Talents, which he left to be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in merchandiſe for his gaines, who bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with euerlaſting chaines his vnthrifty ſeruant, wicked and ſlouthful. And to euery parable: he ioyneth a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence right worthy &amp; méet to be grauen déeply in our harts. <hi>VVatch therfore be cauſe ye knowe neither the day nor the houre in which the ſonne of man vvil come.</hi> But moreouer,<note place="margin">This doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of our Lord / is to be vrged &amp; beare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in to our mindes.</note> who can ſay that this doctrine vttered by our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour, concerning the laſt age and the iudgement to coome, is comberſome or obſcure? It is ſurely more cleere then the noone day vnto them, that deſire to be wiſe. But vnto them that are blinde alwaies, all things become darknes, becauſe of their owne accorde they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vnto them ſelues eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very extreme darkneſſe. But this diligent carefulnes of our Lord, and alſo this wholeſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb facs="tcp:10066:7"/>
ought to ſtir vp all vs his ſeruants vnto like deſire of godlines, to th'intent that wée may with great faithfulneſſe and diligence, ſtir vp alſo eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole world béeing almoſt all in theſe our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es deeply fallen a ſleep: ſtir the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp (I ſay) ſhake them, and ſharply with erneſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on, vrge them to watch, pray, and to conſider throughly the doctrime of our Sauiour, and finally to mark wel thoſe things that haue béen doon in times paſt and thoſe things alſo that are now doon in theſe our daies.</p>
               <p>Verily thoſe things that were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde by our Lord,<note place="margin">By a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon the prophecy of Chriſte is made ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt.</note> we haue ſeen them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the very things them ſelues, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually &amp; in long courſe of time to haue béen fulfilled. For the holy Citie weri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the gréeuous ſéege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Gentils,</hi> at the length was taken, ſpoiled, ſet on fire &amp; vtterly deſtroyed, ſcarcely any few tokens or prints remaining therof. But thoſe Iewes that periſhed not by famin, peſtilence, and the ſword: were taken cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue by the Romains, and diſperſed into all nations throughout the whole world. And alſo the <hi>Goſpel of the kingdome,</hi> in deſpite of the Iewes &amp; Gentiles, and euen in deſpite of hel gates, hath béen
<pb facs="tcp:10066:7"/>
receiued throughout the whole world.</p>
               <p>Furthermore we haue ſeen, that there hath burſt out of the déep pit of hel,<note place="margin">Apoca. 9.</note> thoſe great hepes of <hi>falſe prophets thoſe dead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly locuſts,</hi> which with moſte corrupt and new kinde of doctrine, he hath troubled, vexed, rent in péeces, ſeduced, yea and all ſo repleniſhed with moſte vnſpeakable calamities, the whole Church of Chriſte. But if you as yet ſée not theſe things: con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider more erneſtly, what I ſhall now ſay.<note place="margin">The found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is corrupted.</note> The ſimplicitie and integritie of the olde and Apoſtolike doctrine was in that deadly time vtterly corrupted. It ſemed, and is yet now adiudged by thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, to be a doctrine very vile, vnſéemly, and nothing Catholik, which béeing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the moſte ſacred Goſpell and moſte ſimply and plainly ſet foorth vnto all men according to the example of the Apoſtles, dooth teach, that the faithful are iuſtified by the onely grace of God, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rew faith in Chriſte, or that ſinners are acquited from damnation, their ſinnes forgiuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and euerlaſting life obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God. which benefits they receiue by faith onely and doo ſhew foorth &amp; teſtify their true faith by good woorks. So ſhall it ſéem vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:8"/>
a matter vnaduiſed and nothing plain, if thou ſay that the rule of Chriſte alone is a moſte abſolute rule of true faith and good life, alſo that Chriſte alone ſuffiſeth vnto the godly. And that he alone remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>the Hed, the King, the high preeſt,</hi> of the Churche, in which he is preſent and which he ruleth very wel with his ſpirite and power, euen vnto the end of the world: that the Church cleueth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, honoreth him in <hi>Spirite and trueth:</hi> that the ſame worſhippeth him, not in elements, or corruptible things, but in glory, &amp; at the right hand of God the father. If thou doo thus beleeue, &amp; doo thus plainly and ſimply co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe thy faith: thou ſhalt be accounted nothing Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, yea ſuſpected of hereſy, or rather a very Heretick indéed. For héerunto thou muſt ad, that Chriſte indeed dooth iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs, but not fréely. For <hi>Our merits</hi> muſt come to, and ſo our ſaluation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is made perfect. And therfore by all menes poſſible, they impugne and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this propoſition as hereticall name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That Sinners are iuſtified by onely faith in Chriſte, and not by the vvorks of the lawe.</hi> Moreouer they teach vs to ſpeake more Catholikly and to frame
<pb facs="tcp:10066:8"/>
our talke in this wiſe, namely that men haue their ſinnes in déed forgiuen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Chriſte: but not without the Key graunted vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Préeſts, which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully employed in <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> That mennes ſinnes are indéed pardoned, as touching the fault: but not as touching the pain, which pain (ſay they) is taken away or miniſtred by <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> or by the <hi>Popes pardons.</hi> And the belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers are ſaued indeed, but yet their ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les muſt firſt be wel ſodden and purged with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Holy vvater.</hi> They ad moreouer, that in very deed the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſte is the rule of true faith and good life: but not altogither perfect. But that the want therof is patched vp with liuely <hi>Traditions,</hi> and by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the <hi>councels</hi> and <hi>Fathers.</hi> That the rule of <hi>Munks</hi> are moſte alowable. and moſte perfect, becauſe (forſooth) they are in the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That Chriſt in déed is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hieſt hed in Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but that he in earth hath placed in his-ſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> with fulnes of power to be the hed of his Church. So that they whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch doo not acknowledge this hed, cannot inioy Chriſte in Heauen: for that we ought (vnder pain of damnation) to be
<pb facs="tcp:10066:9"/>
ſubiect to the Biſhop of <hi>Roome.</hi> So they graunt that Chriſte is in déed in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with his Father, an interceſſor and mediator for the faithful: yet they ad by and by: But he is not a mediator alone: For the ſame thing alſo is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto the merits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saints in Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo that by their menes alſo they cauſe our Lord to extend his mercy vnto ſinners calling vpon the names of the Saints. So they graunt that Chriſte is to be worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; trueth: but yet they affirme, that he is neuertheleſſe to be worſhiped with golde, with ſiluer, and all kindes of precioꝰ things,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4. Daniel. 11. Acts. 17.</note> that are to be offered and dedicated to the ornament of temples. So they ſay, that the faithful doo indéed worſhip Chriſte at the right hand of the father in glory: but that he neuertheleſſe muſt be adored alſo and worſhipped vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the forme of bread, in their Chappelꝭ, in their Alters, in their Temples, in their ſtore boxes and Pixes: when by the power of God, and of the woords of conſecration, the ſubſtance of bread and wine is turned, yea tranſubſtantiated in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of the body and blood of Chriſte, no one iot of the ſubſtance of the bread and wine remaining, but onely
<pb facs="tcp:10066:9"/>
the very accidents and outward ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that appéer. Therfore, that Chriſte is to be worſhipped héer, euen héer on the earth, and vnder the elements and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde creatures, they doo erneſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffirme by the traditions of the Popes, <hi>Innocencius, Honorius</hi> and <hi>Vrbanus,</hi> and doo euen poynt him out, as it were with the finger in the earth, heere, and there, moreouer in the deſert, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places, in their Clauſters, &amp; in thoſe their monaſteries. Yea farthermore, to th'intent that the admonition of Ieſus Chriſte our Lord, might not be obſcure or dark, ſaying in the Goſpel. <hi>(They shall ſaye vnto you: beholde heere is Chriſte, beholde he is there, beholde he is in the deſert, beholde he is in the ſtore boxes, or in the ſecret places)</hi> rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about the Pix or litle Sacrament box, they write in great golden letters. <hi>Heer vvorship thou God.</hi> If in any place out of Roome they doo open their Romain pil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gremage <hi>(Ein Romfart)</hi> that is to ſay, if any where they happen to lay out thoſe their indulgences and Pardons to ſale for merchandiſe, then again in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frunt of their Scrips, ſatchels, boxes and ſhops of pardons, they write in great gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:10066:10"/>
letters. <hi>Heer is ful remiſſion of all ſinnes,</hi> and theſe things truely are wel knowen to all men throughout Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endome. But what dooth Chriſte our Lord ad moreouer vnto thoſe things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go not forth, do not beleeue them, beholde I haue tolde you before.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, we haue heard and ſéene in more then a thouſand places, great fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miracles to haue bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrought before dum Images, and before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread turned into God. And all things were doon to this end that theſe new &amp; Doctor like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crées of the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread, of the worſhipping of Images, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuocati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of Saints, and the purchaſing the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits of Saints,<note place="margin">The perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the Church of Chriſte.</note> might be ſet foorth &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to the faithful. But he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil not beléeue theſe things, or ſhall in any iot ſpeake againſt them: is by and by ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vp to priſon, &amp; to execucion of death. We haue learned out of hiſtories, that there hath béen neuer at any time ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp againſt the people of God, any perſecution more greeuous, of longer continuance, and finally alſo more cruel then this laſt by Antichriſt. The afflicti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the people of God in <hi>Egipt</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not abooue two hundred yeres. It is
<pb facs="tcp:10066:10"/>
written in déed that they were in <hi>Egipt</hi> and on their iourney iij. hundred yeeres. But all this time is not aſcribed to the perſecution of the <hi>Iſraelits.</hi> But the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, which they ſuſtained vnder the <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> were very ſhort.</p>
               <p>The captiuitie of <hi>Babilon</hi> was ended within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of lxx. yeeres. The afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Antioche</hi> and <hi>Greece</hi> was contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within certain bonds. Moreouer the ten perſecutions of the primatiue church, laſted thrée hundred yéeres, euen to the reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great. And they had in the mean while certain breathing ſpaces, certain reſpits, and quiet times.</p>
               <p>But ſince the time in which the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome</hi> inuaded the kingdom of Chriſte, &amp; began vſurpingly to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the rule of the Church, and laſtly to chalenge to him ſelf the fulnes of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: there was then no reſt at the end of lxx. yéeres &amp; abooue. None, or very ſhort truces, but continuall laying of trappes and ſnares, perpetuall practiſes and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as it were) euerlaſting. The ſharp and cruel Inquiſicion was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the blood of the faithful: that is to ſay, a more rigorus way, to enquire
<pb facs="tcp:10066:11"/>
againſt the faithful, then euer was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, by the Emperour <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> ſuch as was neuer ſéen in any age or time from the beginning of the world. Heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto is mixed <hi>Excommunication,</hi> the ſtrong ſinew of perſecution. This kinde of perſecution, hath ſhaken the moſte mightie Kings, the <hi>Henries</hi> and <hi>Fride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks,</hi> and their children and nephewes, the <hi>Levviſes,</hi> and innumerable princes. With the ſame, the Pope hath ſubdued vnto him ſelf, people otherwiſe very fierce and couragious. The ſame hath ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken away the moſte holy and moſte lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned men in the world: and hath compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſimpler and more vnlearned ſort, either vtterly to kéep ſilence, or els to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſemble. For at the length by this his outragious tirany: be made kings and princes thrall and obedient vnto him, ſo that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (by hepes) haue gréedely héer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore, and now doo ſtil beare armor in defence of this new God, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and by violence to force vppon all men, his new Religion. I doo fain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing héerin, neither reliue I my gaule, neither ſpeak I any thing for hatered, or fauour of any man. God, the iudge of all men is my witnes in this behalf.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:11"/>Moreouer, all hiſtoryes bothe olde and new, doo make mention of theſe things. Finally what is doon in our daies, and with what perſecutions are oppreſſed, not the blaſphemers, not the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Religion, not the adulterers, not thoſe that are defiled with inceſt, with whordomes, with fornications (to ſpeak nothing of more filthy acts) not murderers, not Sorſerers, not Traitors, not deceitful perſones, couetous men, V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, or Theeues and oppreſſors of wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and fatherleſſe children: but the profeſſors of the true Religion, and the confutors of the Popes abominations.</p>
               <p>They that doo not ſée it, and with gréef mark it, are more blinde then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they heard this ſaying <hi>(Chriſt when he commeth, shall hee do mo mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racles then this man hath doon?</hi> (and when alſo the thing it ſelf did beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the meane while moſte apparant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, yet by no meanes did they beléeue in him. Yea, how is it, that they more fréendly doo ſpare and fauour Théeues, and murderers, then the loouers of the Euangelicall trueth? The Iewes are ſuffered and borne with all, the Turks, the Saraſens, and the moſte naughty
<pb facs="tcp:10066:12"/>
and moſte hurtful men of all. The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pellers alone beeing vnharmful, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thought worthy of any pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe onely ſéeme méet to be diſpatched out of the way without any mercy. So that héerin alſo thou maiſt perceiue Chriſtes ſaying to be verified. <hi>You shallbe hated of all men for my names ſake.</hi> Alſo <hi>The time wil come, that he, vvhich shal kil you shall ſeem to doo honour vnto God.</hi> Again who is ignorant, with how great ſtraitnes euen in the Papiſtrie moſte cheefly in the Abbies, are vexed, men not altogither euil, and many with troubled conſciences? Who knoweth not that God and godly men, not a few, pine away euen with very ſorow? But who ſhall recite vnto vs the age, of late daies and in this our time, notable and famous in ſignes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders and ſtraunge tokens? I wil not now ſpeak of the ciuil and forain warres, ſeditions, ſchiſmes, ſects, debates, tumults, trecheries, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, vnfaithfulnes, wiked leages, mens crueltie moſte extreme, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions moſte horrible, and thoſe not a few.</p>
               <p>Of theſe things who cannot gather, that faith and loue is become colde vpon
<pb facs="tcp:10066:12"/>
earth, and that extreme wickednes boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the harts of men? Furthermore, we ſee that the world at this day, beeing in ſuch horrible dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, is moſte abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſtuffed and repleniſhed with ſuch as deſpiſe God, and make a mock of all trueth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the moſte religious (that is to ſay) they, vnto whom this name is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and who haue their liuing &amp; gaines by Religion, make Religion it ſelf a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry game. Vnto vs it is a good perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaid that moſte holy one) which maketh vs Lords ouer the whole world. And I am a ſhamed, to rehearſe thoſe things that are ſpoken by learned and religious fathers in this kinde of matter. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures béeing a company of Swine, doo laugh and pleſantly make a ieſt at the looue of vertues, and at the calamities, which the faithful doo patiently ſuſtain for Religions ſake, at the immortalitie of the ſoule, and the reſurrection of the body, alſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rewardꝭ of the godly and puniſhments of the wicked, and at thoſe things whatſoeuer, which are ſpoken conſerning ſpirituall and heauenly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. More ouer, we ſée that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all ſorts one with another are déep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly drowned in a careleſſe ſecuritie: and
<pb facs="tcp:10066:13"/>
that therefore reigneth among them a monſterous looue of ſurfetting and drun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kennes.</p>
               <p>Moſte men doo promiſe to them ſelues many hundred yéeres yet to come, and therfore they make mery or els with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſimulation doo let paſſe all prechings of of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, of faſting, and of ſobriety, of faith and of prayers of the end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world now at hand, &amp; of the eſchuing the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of euils.<note place="margin">Gene. 18.</note> But if any doo ſomewhat fréely reprooue theſe Swine for their ſhameful filthines: by and by he heareth that, which <hi>Loth</hi> heard at the hands of his Citizins the <hi>Sodomites. Thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt hether as a ſtranger, and wilt thou now be a Iudge among vs?</hi> But (I pray you) which be the daies of <hi>Noe</hi> &amp; <hi>Loth,</hi> if theſe be not they? All good admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the very woord of God it ſelf are moſte extremly deſpiſed. What remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth therfore (ye fathers and brethern honorable in Chriſte, and moſte déerly belooued) but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the laſt day of our Lord is not very far abſent: and that therfore all our ſhéep committed to our charge, are to be exited and ſtirred vp vnto a diligent and ſober watchfulneſſe? In vain ſhall we cry out, when the very
<pb facs="tcp:10066:13"/>
day falleth vppon vs. For it ſhall inuade vs vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſudain, like vnto a lightning.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, the mindes of all men muſt betimes afore hand be made ready, and verily with none other doctrin, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſame of Ieſus Chriſte our Lord, of which I haue hitherto intreated with as much breuitie as I could. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I doo aduiſe all men,<note place="margin">The day &amp; yeere of the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cannot be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> héerin er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to take heed, leſt in ſcanning and ſifting out of the time or els the day or yéer of the laſt end, we be to bolde or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to raſh: as ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e lewd felowes there haue béen of late yéeres, who haue (as it were) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their finger poynted out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day and the yéer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> finall iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, therin ſhewi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g forth their folly worthy to be moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked of all men. Chriſte Ieſus our Lord, the iudge of all men, who, according to his Godhed,<note place="margin">Mark. 13.</note> vnderſtandeth all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of his father, ſaid in the goſpel of S. <hi>Mark. Of that day and time no man knoweth, no, not the Angels which are in Heauen, neither the Sonne him ſelf</hi> (as touching his humain nature) <hi>but the father alone.</hi> And a little after. <hi>Ye knowe not when that time shalbe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therfore as the Lord him ſelf hath taught vs to ſpeak: ſo let vs ſpeak, and
<pb facs="tcp:10066:14"/>
ſay. <hi>Take heed, watch and pray. For ye knovve not when your Lord wil come, in the euening or at midnight, at the Cock crovving, or in the davvning, leſt if he come vnwares, hee finde you, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. VVherfore vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye shall ſe theſe things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to paſſe vvhich I haue tolde you before, should happen: knovve ye that the kingdome of God is at hand. And therfore look vp and lift vp your heds. For your redemption dravveth nigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhort doctrin of Chriſte our Lord may ſuffiſe vnto his Diſciples, béeing careful and diligent, and not delighting in long proces. And becauſe I dout not but that ſome yet doo deſire and look for a more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful diſcourſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe things: we wil therfore bréefly ouerrun the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of bleſſed <hi>Daniel</hi> vpon this matter.<note place="margin">The ꝓphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el touching the end of the world and the times of the laſt age.</note> Him we chooſe out among others, and before others, becauſe our Sauiour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating of the deſtruction of the Citie and the world, ſent vs back to this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, whoſe prophecy we ſhould eaſely vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Daniel. 7.</note> if we did giue good héed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. <hi>Daniel</hi> therfore béeing taught by the heauenly viſion: rehearceth foure <hi>Monarchies,</hi> that ſhould ariſe in the
<pb facs="tcp:10066:14"/>
world, among which: the laſt be calleth a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which, (he ſaith) ſhould haue <hi>ten hornes,</hi> among which: one <hi>Little horne</hi> ſpringing vp ſhould caſt down iij. of them and that the ſame ſhould growe vp in maruelous forſe, and far excel all the reſt. The ſame alſo (ſaith he) had the eyes of a man, and a mouth ſpeaking great things, and that he made gréeuous and perpetuall war againſt the Saints, ouer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e alſo he eaſely preuailed and reighneth moſt puiſauntly and moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenciouſly, vntil the ſeats were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and iudgement placed in throne.</p>
               <p>For then was all that kingdome rent in péeces, and the beaſt thrown into the fire to be burnt with euerlaſting flames. Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> expounding theſe things ſaith. <hi>By the fourth Beaſt, the Prophet vnderſtandeth the Romaine Empire, vvhich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e neither calleth a Lion, as the Empire of Babilon, neither a beare as of Perſia, neither a Parde, as of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia, but he calleth him a Beaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the intent that vvhat ſoeuer vvee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine moſte fierce and cruell in beaſts: the ſame vve may vnderſtand by the Romains.</hi> Thus much ſaith S. <hi>Ierome.</hi> But ſéeing <hi>Daniel</hi> him ſelf hath ſowen
<pb facs="tcp:10066:15"/>
abrode the ſéedes of the right expoſition héerof: by folowing the things them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and conferring of hiſtoryes: I will ſhowe the interpretation of this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall viſion, not inforced: but take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the woords of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet &amp; out of the very things them ſelues, &amp; therfore eaſy and apparaunt of the owne accord, Verily, it is wel knowen, that the <hi>Romain</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire hath raged ouer the whole earth with furious woodnes more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſtly.</p>
               <p>For, if I ſhould omit to make mention how that vnder this Empire (whoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſals were the <hi>Herods) Ihon Baptiſt</hi> was beheaded, and at the laſt Chriſte him ſelf was crucified vnder <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour (<hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> beeing then Lieutenaunt for the <hi>Romains</hi>) all the Apoſtles of Chriſte were alſo moſte gréeuouſly afflicted, and at the length moſt cruelly ſlain, and the Primitiue Church (with the x. moſte fierce perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with fire and ſword) worne away yea, and almoſte vtterly conſumed: yet who knoweth not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was almoſte no parte of the world inhabited, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into the moſte raging weapons of the <hi>Romains</hi> haue not broken in, and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame (with their filthy luſt, in
<pb facs="tcp:10066:15"/>
tollerable pride and vnſatiable coueteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes) haue at the length vtterly deuoured it? But the iuſt Lord, in due time hath recompenced blood thirſty <hi>Rome</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her deſerts,<note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed.</note> and by diuiſion hath made concord, and ſo alſo hath rent her ſtrength in ſunder, which thing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hath ſignified by the x. hornes. For, while the prouinſes reuolted from the <hi>Romain</hi> Empire, and ſome of them cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Kings vnto them ſelues: and other ſome bare armour againſt the imperiall Citie, and the Emperours them ſelues, within few yéeres it came to paſſe, that the Citie béeing Lady of the whole world: was taken &amp; ſacked of barbarous people, and alſo made a mocking ſtock, and at the laſte ſet on fire and deſtroyed by <hi>Tottilas</hi> of <hi>Oſtgothia,</hi> a prince wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eternall reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, and a moſte famous ſeruant of God.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time and before alſo, when the Cittie was come into the hands of <hi>Genſiricus</hi> the <hi>VVandall,</hi> and when immediatly afterward it was gouerned by <hi>Odacer</hi> king of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> who bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead: it was ſubiect to <hi>Djetricus</hi> of <hi>Verona</hi> &amp; the <hi>Oſtgothes,</hi> all that while there was no lawful Emperour or <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:16"/>
in <hi>Italy,</hi> as afore at <hi>Rome.</hi> Only at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the Cittie of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> the great y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte godly prince, reigned the Emperours of the Eaſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>Ioannes Paleologus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>huel</hi> béeing the laſt Emperour of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> (except one) did in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Florence</hi> acknowledge <hi>Eugenius</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnto whome he there ſubmitted him ſelf &amp; his alſo. This was doon in the yéere of our Lord <hi>1439.</hi> For,<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantinople <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>oued &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerthrowne</note> ſtraight waies his ſonne <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the vij. ſurnamed <hi>Draco,</hi> béeing ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dued by <hi>Mahumedes</hi> the Emperour of the <hi>Turcks,</hi> loſt his Cittie, his life, and his Empire. So that for a iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that moſte filthy reuolting and backſliding: the moſte auncient Empire of <hi>Grecia,</hi> that had ſtand vpright <hi>1119.</hi> yéeres, was by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Turcks</hi> thrown down and very cruelly ſubuerted. This cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie happened in the yéere of our Lord <hi>1453,</hi> So that from the councel of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> to the reuolting: were onely xiiij. yéeres betwéene. And S. <hi>Ierome</hi> in his Cronicles noteth that the Citie of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> was dedicated by <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> in the yéere of our Lord <hi>334.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider héer, in the meane while (ye
<pb facs="tcp:10066:16"/>
worthy men) the goodnes and Iuſtice of our Lord God, and therwith all his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uellous trueth.<note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of God beſtowed vppon Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantine the greae.</note> The bleſſed Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> faithfully ſerued the true God and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte in roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, and ſuppreſſing of all hetheniſh Idolatrie and ſuperſtition &amp; on the other ſide in planting, ſpreading abrode, and eſtabliſhing of Chriſtian religion, and for that cauſe (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> maketh mention) God that plentiful rewarder of all good men, was willing to adorne him not onely with eternall ioy in Heauen: but alſo with moſte ample glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne vpon earth.</p>
               <p>For he gaue vnto him the moſte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citie in the world, and a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and moſt inuincible kingdome. For, God drawing him away from that fatal land of <hi>Italy,</hi> and from the bloody Cittie of <hi>Rome</hi> (which alſo, it is likly the prince him ſelf to haue abhorred) brought him vnto <hi>Bizantium</hi> in <hi>Thracia,</hi> where he built a famoꝰ Citie of his owne name which was vnto his poſteritie euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world a moſte worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of ſo very good &amp; moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a Prince. Wherby it come to paſſe by a certaine prouidence of God, and (as it
<pb facs="tcp:10066:17"/>
were) by a certain prophecy, that it ſhuld take the name of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> him ſelf, and alſo of that good chriſtian woman <hi>Conſtantia.</hi> Like as ſome report, <hi>Rome</hi> to haue taken name of <hi>Romulus,</hi> that ſlew his brother, or (as ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſay) <hi>a robore tirannico &amp; immenſa ſuperbia,</hi> that is of the tiranicall force, and vnmeſurable pride (what if ye ad, <hi>vom braemen v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumen vnd be ſchiſſen</hi>) with which it hath been a raging enemye againſt the whole worlde bothe ſpiritually and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally. Aſſuredly all hiſtoryes doo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that our Lord God bare a ſinguler great fauour vnto the Citie of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> One matter onely will I reſite.</p>
               <p>After the decay of the <hi>Romain</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, how ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world run togither with mutuall warres amonge them ſelues, &amp; moſt kingdomes taſted of meruelous alterations: yet neuertheles the kingdom of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſtedfaſt and vnmoouable, giuing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repulſe vnto barbarous nations, and alſo to the very <hi>Saraſines,</hi> beeing ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes otherwiſe moſte mightie &amp; fierce. But at the length beeing vtterly void of Gods protection: it was laid open to be ſpoyled and trodden vnder foote by the
<pb facs="tcp:10066:17"/>
                  <hi>Turks,</hi> at what time the Princes of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> béeing deceiued by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>genius</hi> the Pope, to the great calamitie of moſte mightie Princes. (For at that ſeaſon by the vnhappy councel of <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rathe,</hi> he ouerthrew <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the moſte victorious King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> with all his whole hoſte) departing in the councell of <hi>Florence,</hi> from their true head Chriſte, acknowledged the Pope of <hi>Roome</hi> to be the true Vicar of Chriſte, on earth, and the lawful ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſor of <hi>Peeter</hi> (I reherſe the woords of <hi>Platina</hi>) to occupy the chéefeſt and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place in the world, whom the Church bothe of the Eaſt and alſo of the Weſt ought of duty to obey.</p>
               <p>But ſéeing that theſe things haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to this moſte noble ond moſte an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Citie, through the iuſt iudgement of God: let men take héed in theſe dayes what they doo, that béeing deliuered tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the tuicion and diligence of good Princes, from this <hi>Romain</hi> beaſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, proud, inſatiable in blood and riches, filthy and deceiuable: yet wil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain throwe down the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vnder his féet, and to be ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:10066:18"/>
Sith all kinds of legerdemain.</p>
               <p>But now I return to <hi>Daniel.</hi> It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péereth out of hiſtories (as I was about to tel) that in the Weſt, within <hi>Roome</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> beeing the auncient ſeat of the empire, there was no <hi>Caeſar</hi> or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, all the time from the deſolation of the Weſt Empire, vnto the dayes of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, which was thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yéeres and more. For the Hornes, that grue vp by the diuiſion of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi> Empire, béeing diuers and many, did fiercely fight togither, and ſlew one another. So that <hi>Roome</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> was gouerned now by the weſt <hi>Gothes</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward by the <hi>VVandalles,</hi> after that by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> ſo by the Eaſt <hi>Gothes,</hi> then by the <hi>Greeks:</hi> and at the length the <hi>Lombards</hi> alſo, and <hi>Frenchmen</hi> attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Empire.</p>
               <p>And during this vnhappy time, while the frantick Prinres ſlewe one another with mutuall wounds, there ſprung vp in the middeſt of this contention, that baſe and deſpiſed litle Horne that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſpeaketh of, namely a pariſh Préeſt of <hi>Roome,</hi> who a litle before this time through moſte wicked deuiſes &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, began to be in authoritie: which
<pb facs="tcp:10066:18"/>
helped him exceedingly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> attainment of the Empire. For now he was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted almoſte of all men in the weſt parts for the vniuerſall paſtor, as Biſhop of that place, which (after long contention had, firſt with the Churches of <hi>Africa,</hi> and afterwarde of <hi>Conſtantinople) Phocas</hi> the Emperour, altogither an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and vnfortunate Prince, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to be chéefeſt and head of all Churches in the world.</p>
               <p>Therfore now the Popes iudgements and decrées were of great authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong princes, as of a man altogither A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike: who neuertheleſſe hitherto was equall with other Biſhops, and had no princely ſuperioritie, and therfore, was a baſe and deſpiſed litle horne.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Daniel</hi> dooth not let to tel, by what meanes, that baſe perſon not accounted of, who was once vnder the ſubiection of the <hi>Romain</hi> Princes, is now ſtarted vp to ſo great a dignitie &amp; power,<note place="margin">The little horne ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth iii. hornes.</note> namly by the ouerthrowe of thrée Hornes in that ſharp conflict of the other Hornes. And héer I would haue you to note dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Daniel,</hi> in declaring of this matter, vſed not one o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly woord but thrée.</p>
               <p>For he ſaith, that the Hornes were
<pb facs="tcp:10066:19"/>
pluct a way, brought lowe &amp; fel down. Namely, that one of the thrée hornes was pluckt awaye, an other brought lowe, and the third fel down. For <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Room</hi> the ſecond of that name, a <hi>Cirian</hi> born, and a man very wittie and ſubtile, did excomunicate <hi>Leo Iſauricus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> (béeing a good and other wiſe a ſtrong Prince) for taking away the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages out of the temples of Chriſtians, whom alſo he plucked away and draue him out of <hi>Italy.</hi> Héerin reigned the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Oſtgothes,</hi> men barbarous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Clxxv yéeres. But theſe were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very expert in the affaires of war. And <hi>Narſes</hi> a ſkilful and mightie warrier, béeing ſent by the princes of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> draue them clean out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and he him ſelf ruled <hi>Italy,</hi> as Liuetenant for the Prince of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, <hi>Longinus</hi> brought a new kinde of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into <hi>Italy</hi> called the <hi>Exarchate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Exar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate af Ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenna.</note> ſuch a one as was the Depu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty and Viceroy in <hi>Italy</hi> in place of the Prince of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> He was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Exarchus,</hi> who had his ſeat at <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna</hi> and not at <hi>Roome,</hi> becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:19"/>
very filthy, and (as it were) deſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late, by meanes of the waſte &amp; deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doon by the <hi>Gothes.</hi> And after <hi>Narces</hi> and <hi>Baſilius, Rome</hi> had neuer Conſuls, nor ſenat lawfully aſſembled. But the Romain ſtate béeing vtterly waſted: was gouerned a long time by the rule of a <hi>Grecian,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Exarchus</hi> ſent from <hi>Rauenna.</hi> And it was not called the <hi>Exarchate</hi> of <hi>Roome:</hi> but of <hi>Rauenna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But after that <hi>Leo</hi> the Gréek Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope had perſwaded all the Cities of <hi>Italy</hi> to reuolt: they began to chuſe them Dukes to rule ouer them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it came to paſſe immediatly, that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting away the gouernment of the <hi>Exar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chate,</hi> they ſlew through ſedition <hi>Paule</hi> the <hi>Exarchus</hi> togither with his Sonne at <hi>Rauenna,</hi> and expelled the <hi>Grecians</hi> out of <hi>Italy.</hi> And ſo this horn was pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked away.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, Pope <hi>Zacharias,</hi> wheras he was falſely eſteemed by the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> and other nations, to be the true A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtolike and vniuerſall biſhop on earth, was choſen vmpire, to pronounce whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were more worthy of the kingdome <hi>Hildericus</hi> or <hi>Pipin</hi> the dwarf. But he
<pb facs="tcp:10066:20"/>
brought lowe the true King <hi>Hildericus,</hi> in place of whom hée exalted <hi>Pipine</hi> béeing the chéef ruler of his houſe.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, <hi>Stephen</hi> the ſucceſſor of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> ſecond of that name (the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe béeing giuen to the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and alſo in deſpite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Greeks</hi>) receiued for a reward of his wicked fact, the <hi>Exar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate</hi> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> lately made deſolate by the practiſes of the Pope. And ſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the thrée Hornes was brought lowe, and the litle horne was exalted, into a higher eſtate. Furthermore, now after theſe commeth <hi>Charles</hi> the great, the ſonne of <hi>Pipin</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwarf, who beeing called foorth by Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> in to <hi>Italy</hi> againſt the <hi>Lumhards,</hi> at <hi>Papia</hi> or <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinum</hi> 'beſéeged and took <hi>Deſiderius</hi> the laſt king of the <hi>Lombards</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; ſo o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerthrew and rooted vp the kingdome of <hi>Lombardy.</hi> Wherby the third of the thrée Hornes, may very wel be ſaid to haue fallen downe. But the Citie of <hi>Roome</hi> was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <hi>Charles</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Saint <hi>peeter,</hi> and to the biſhop there, the ſucceſſor of Saint <hi>Peeter</hi> and to the <hi>Romain Church.</hi> And thoſe things, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch his elders before him had giuen late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the ſame he enlarged and confirmed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:20"/>But before I procéed to other things partaining to this matter: I cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the expoſition of <hi>Daniel,</hi> &amp; the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of that moſte famous and godly man <hi>Ebarhardus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge</hi> concerning Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, and other Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who about the yéer of our Lord <hi>1240.</hi> in a common Parlement of the kingdome (as it is mentioned by <hi>Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> in his ſeuenth Book of Cronicles) thus ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Theſe mightie holy Préeſts of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon</hi> deſire to reign alone. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide to haue any equall. They wil not ceaſſe til they haue brought all things vnder their ſubiection, and ſit in the Temple of God, and lifted vp abooue all whatſoeuer is woorſhiped. Their hunger for riches, their thirſtineſſe for honor is vnſatiable. The more thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt to a couetous man: the more dooth he couet and deſire. Reach him thy fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and he will couet for thy whole ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, We wax the worſſe (euen all the ſorte of vs) through immoderate libertie. He that is the Seruant of Seruants, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be the Lord of Lords, euen as though he were God him ſelf. He diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth
<pb facs="tcp:10066:21"/>
the holy aſſemblies and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of his bretheren, yea, of thoſe that be Lords and rulers ouer him. Hée is afraid leſt he ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled, to yeld account of thoſe things whiche hee dooth daly more and more againſt the lawes. He ſpeaketh great things, as though he were a God. He imagineth in his hart new deuiſes, to the intent he might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a Kingdome to him ſelf. Hée chaungeth lawes, confirmeth his owne, defileth, robbeth, ſpoyleth, defraudeth, killeth, euen hee that wicked outcaſt, whom they vſe to call <hi>Antichriſte.</hi> In whoſe forhed is written the name of blaſphemy <hi>(I am God, I cannot erre)</hi> he ſitteth in the temple of God, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth far &amp; néer. But as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſecrets of holy Scriptures, he that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth let him vnderſtand. The learned ſhall vnderſtand, but all the wicked ſhal doo wickedly and ſhall not vnderſtand. And by and by after this. The maieſtie of the people of <hi>Roome,</hi> by whiche in times paſt the whole world was gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is taken away from the Earth, and the Empire is returned back into <hi>Aſia.</hi> The Eaſt ſhall beare dominion again, and the Weſt ſhalbe brought vnder ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.
<pb facs="tcp:10066:21"/>
The kingdome was multiplied, and the higheſt gouernment of things, is now diſperſed in to many, cut in ſunder, diminiſhed (I wil not ſay) torn all to pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Ciuil diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are ſowed abrode for euer. And wée ſée no end of deadly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. The name of Emperour is but a vain name, and but a ſhadowe only.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>There are now ten Kings at once, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue parted amongſt them the whole earth béeing héertofore the <hi>Romain</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, not to rule and gouern it: but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it. The ten Hornes (which ſeemed incredible to Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) that is to ſay. The <hi>Turcks,</hi> the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptians,</hi> the <hi>Africans,</hi> the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> the <hi>Englishmen,</hi> the <hi>Germaines,</hi> the <hi>Sicilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> the <hi>Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> haue in poſſeſſion the prouinces of <hi>Rome,</hi> and haue rooted out the <hi>Romaines,</hi> that inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the ſame. And vnder theſe grewe vp a litle Horne, which had eyes, and a mouth ſpeaking preſumptuous things. He bringeth into ſubiection vnder him thrée Kingdoms moſte cheefly, that is to ſay. <hi>Sicily, Italy</hi> &amp; <hi>Germany,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth them to ſerue him. He vexeth the people of Chriſte, and the Saints of God with his intollerable ſoueraintie
<pb facs="tcp:10066:22"/>
He turneth all things vpſide down, bothe things diuine and humain. He attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth matters horrible &amp; excecrable. What can be more euident, then this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? All the miracles and prodigious wunders, of whiche our Hauenly mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter did admoniſh vs (read ye the chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) were wrought a great while ago, in which preſumption &amp; viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce poſſeſſe all thinges. Good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are toſſed to &amp; fro with all reprochefulnes and pouertie. All right is confounded, and Lawes periſh, there is no faith in men, no peace, no gentleneſſe, no ſhame, no trueth, &amp; there withall no ſafetie alſo, no gouernment, no reſt at all from euil men, all the whole earth is in a whurlyburly, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res doo rage on euery ſide. all nations are vp in armour, aſſaulting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Cities néere bordering do fight togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Kingdomes are ouerthrowen, and Cities doo vtterly periſh not onely with Swoord and fire, but alſo with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Earthquakes and ouerflowings of waters, and with often diſeſes and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Maruelous wunders happen eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in all the Elements of the world. The aire is infected, corrupted, and vnholſome through vnſaciable rain,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:22"/>
ſometime with vnprofitable drought, ſometime with colde, ſometime with to-much heats. Neither dooth the Earth yéeld any foyſon vnto man, neither the corne, nor trées, nor Vines haue any fruteful increace. And though in their bloughth they giue great ſhowe: yet in Harueſt they bring no frute. Cattel and beaſtes dye vppon the earth, Birds in the aire and the fiſhes in the waters. Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Starres and darknes of the Sun, the coloure of the Moone, the ſuddain and vnaccuſtomable falling of the ſhooting Starres, the heauens ouerſpred with blood, confoundeth the mindes of men with dreadful terrour. through the wrath of God againſt men, there rageth Swoord, fire. hungar and ſiknes. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe the vngodly acknowledge not the Iuſtice of God, but rather increace more and more in euil. In ſo much that they haue eyes and ſee not.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And this haue I reſited woord by woord out of the Chronicle of <hi>Auentinus,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che if any of you deſire to read, ye ſhall finde it in the Copie of <hi>Ingolſtadius</hi> printed in the yéer of our Lord. <hi>1554.</hi> in the lefe <hi>684.</hi> and <hi>685.</hi> &amp;c. All theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Archchbiſhop agrée very well
<pb facs="tcp:10066:23"/>
to our matter and expound the ſame. And it appéereth, that I am not alone of this opinion that he putteth other Kingdoms in place of the thrée Hornes. Whiche thing I commit to the Iudgement of the reader. With my expoſition accordeth the number of the beaſts name. <hi>Apoca. 13.</hi> of which I haue elſwhere diſcourſed more at large.</p>
               <p>Now let vs return to our <hi>Daniell,</hi> bréefly to expound that alſo which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth. But thus by caſting down of the thrée hornes, that litle horne menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by <hi>Daniel,</hi> namely that bace Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Chriſte, and euen the Seruant of Seruants, did not onely clime vp to the higheſt top: but alſo became the moſte mightie Prince of that fatall Land of <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 17.</note> and Lord of ſeuen hilled <hi>Room,</hi> and of the Palaice of Antichriſte. The which, he and his repaired and adorned by the ſpace of ſeuen hundred and fiftye yéeres, ſo that olde <hi>Rome</hi> by the help of theſe woorthy Patriarches, may now ſéeme to be new borne again. And héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſéemeth to haue rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">1. Theſſa. 2.</note> who in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> plainly ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This thing onely nowe vvitholding
<pb facs="tcp:10066:23"/>
vntil he be taken out of the way, and than that wicked one shalbe reueled.</hi> Which is aſmuch in effect, as if he had ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This onely that now letteth, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Empire of Roome ſhalbe taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and when <hi>Tocatochon</hi> that is, the ſame impediment ſhalbe taken away, then ſhall the Romain Sea be erected, and in the ſame newe and ſecond ſeate ſhalbe placed the two horned beaſt, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the badge of keyes, and armed with two ſwoords. Neither doo I alone ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this place of <hi>Paule</hi> after this ſort. <hi>Tertulian</hi> did euen ſo expound the ſame abooue fourtéen hundred yeeres ago, who in his book of the reſurrection of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVho shalbe taken away</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>but the Romaine eſtate, vvhoſe depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſcattered in to ten kingdomes shall bring in Antichriſte?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame meaning alſo hath Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> in the eleuenth queſtion to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope / a new King and troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler of king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domes.</note> who manifeſtly calleth Roome by the name of <hi>Babilon,</hi> the ſeat of the Beaſt and of the purple Harlote. And thus the Pope this newe king, béeing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in his kingdome, began euen him ſelf alſo to create kings, and in great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of glory to excel all chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:24"/>
and afterwarde in all kingdomes to make trouble and whurly hurly.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Leo</hi> the thirde Pope of that name, reſtored, or rather raiſed vp anew the Romain deſolate and defaced by the ſpace of thrée hundred yéeres and more, reiecting vtterly the Princes of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> For he appointed <hi>Charles</hi> the French King to be Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: and yet in ſuch ſorte, that beſide the vain name it litle auailed him. For he reſerueth Room to him ſelf, and the chée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt part of <hi>Italy,</hi> which the Gréeks had poſſeſſed, and was called by the name of <hi>Exarchate.</hi> But he graunted vnto <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> a parte of <hi>Italy,</hi> (ſom Romain titles) whiche was recouered from the <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards,</hi> and alſo the empty name of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. Therfore according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Ieſus Chriſte, vttered by <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Apocalips. The Image of the beaſt is ſeen,</hi> ſtirred vp by the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. No dout, the ſame was doon by the marueilous crafty woorkmanſhip of that olde wily Fox. For when all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie looked for Antichriſte about th'end of the Romain Empire, and when he was about the very ſame time riſen vp and had placed him ſelf in the ſeat of god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:24"/>
he going about (as it were) to repaire the dcayed Empire, brought to paſſe, that he was not knowen of the faithful. But, they rather béeing deceiued with his ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle practiſes, looked for a certain (I knowe not what) Antichriſte of <hi>Babilon,</hi> whom in their publiſhed Bookes they declare, ſhould bée yet to come, and whom alſo they earneſtly diſpraiſe.</p>
               <p>Yet ſhould they not miſſe the right mark, if they would with all elder times call Roome that <hi>Babilon,</hi> and in ſteade of time comming to place the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. At the length the ſtock of <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Pipin</hi> béeing rooted out, ſo that the Popes had remaining litle or no help at all from the hande of the french Kings, as in time paſt they had abuſed the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Lombards,</hi> from whom afterwarde they flitted vnto the French men, ſo now they créep in to the fauour of the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> the better to bring their matters about.</p>
               <p>Wherfore the <hi>Othoes</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their Armies, ſet vppon <hi>Italy</hi> with great labour and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pences. Vnder theſe are choſen vij. men, whom they tearme Electors. They chuſe the Emperour. But the Imperiall maieſtie and eſtate is giuen by none
<pb facs="tcp:10066:25"/>
but by the Pope. For now the Popes of Roome had gotten the Monarchie in to their owne hands, wherby alſo within a while after they pluckt away the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire from the <hi>Henries, Frediricks, Levv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,</hi> and many other notable and holy Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> troubling in the meane ſeaſon, and waſting with ſwoord and fire, all the kingdomes in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo that (not without good cauſe) they were called the Children of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
               <p>I wil now ſpeak nothing of the war that was commonly named the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly war,</hi> which was procured moſte chée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly by the induſtrie of the Pope. In that warre were ioyned togither all the nations and kingdomes bothe of the eaſt and of the weſt, moreouer alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> North and of the South. Wherby folowed ſo huge a bloodſhed, that there was neuer at anye time in the worlde any battail fought with more ireful and obſtinate mindes, and with ſo great loſſe of things as this the popes holy battail.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, they began to thruſt out Kings from their auncient inheritances and kingdomes, through treaſons &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and in their places to exalte others
<pb facs="tcp:10066:25"/>
for their owne pleaſure and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe bothe Kings and kingdomes fought moſte fiercely one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another. So they ſtirred vp the Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Princes of other nations, againſt thoſe, whom they accounted for their enemies. So was <hi>Cicily</hi> and <hi>Naples</hi> wreſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the poſteritie of th'Emperour <hi>Friderick</hi> the <hi>Sweuian,</hi> and cruel warre was betwéen the <hi>Germans, Frenchmen</hi> and <hi>Spaniards.</hi> But often times the <hi>French</hi> Kings were lewdly recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the Popes hands.</p>
               <p>In déed <hi>Boniface</hi> the viij. with wun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull impudencie béeing bolde to claim the kingdome of <hi>Fraunce</hi> to be the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the Popes maieſtie: took away the ſame from <hi>Philip</hi> the fair, then King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and gaue it (forſooth) to <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Awſtrey.</hi> But, impoſſible it is, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, in few woords, how ſore this new vnhappy kingdom of the pope, and moſte miſcheuous Monarchy hath ſhaken the whole world. It is ſufficient, to haue at the leaſt wiſe touched theſe things, that by them, as through a lattiſe windowe, yee may ſée, that there is not, or was not
<pb facs="tcp:10066:26"/>
at any time any kingdome in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome more troubleſome, then the Popedome of Roome. The hiſtories doo at large proſecute the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now I return to <hi>Daniel.</hi> let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider <hi>Daniels</hi> moſt perfect and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident deſcription of this new king, and let vs compare the things them ſelues with him, to the intent all men may plainly knowe with out any douting, that the prophecy of <hi>Daniel</hi> is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and ment of none other then of the biſhop of Roome, and of his kingdom, and that all things touching him, are all ready throughly fulfilled. Wherby it commeth to paſſe, that wée can looke for none other thing, but the laſt iudgement and therwithall the end af all things.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe, let vs all watch (as du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bindeth vs) and ſtir vp all men to a circumſpect watchfulneſſe. <hi>The eyes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Danial) of this little horne vvere the eyes of a man.</hi> For this King was throughly exerciſed, wily, deceitful, and furniſhed with all kinde of arts and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. And his retinew excelleth in this facultie all the practicioners of all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And ſurely this facultie hath promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him vnto his kingdome, augmented
<pb facs="tcp:10066:26"/>
his power, couered his wickednes, and keepeth him yet in ſafetie.</p>
               <p>The Prophet addeth further. <hi>His mouth ſpeaketh great things, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous things.</hi> Alſo, <hi>He shall ſpeak meruelous and wunderful things againſt the God of Gods.</hi> So that the prophet dooth meruail greatly at his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency. But (reuerend maiſters and déerly belooued brethren) if yée deſire to heare ſome of his great preſumptuous woords giue eare. I wil reherſe ſome of them vnto you out of their owne bookes.<note place="margin">What thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are taught in the decrees decretals / and gloſes touching the Pope of Rome / his maieſtie and Monar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chie.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Pope</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is aboue all lawes. He may prefer by his owne interpretation equity not write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the lawe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. For he ſeemeth to haue all lawes in the Cofar of his breſt. Therefore, what ſoeuer the Pope alloweth or diſſaloweth, the ſame ought we alſo to alow or diſsalow. Of the iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:10066:27"/>
of the Apoſtolick ſeat no man ought to iudge: neither is it lawful for any man, to correct or repeale the ſentence of the ſame, namely becauſe of the pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macy &amp; ſoueraintie of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main church, giuen from abooue by the benefite of Chriſt in ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsed Peeter the Apoſtle. The Iudge ought not to bee iudged, neither of councel nor of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, nor of the whole clergie, nor of the Kinges, nor of the people. The cauſes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: God would haue to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by man. But without all queſtion, God hath reſerued to his own Iudgement, the high ruler of this Sea: In ſomuche
<pb facs="tcp:10066:27"/>
that if he should cary with him by heapes innumerable people to hel fire, yet no mortall man may preſume, to reprooue his faultes heerin, becauſe he is to iudge all men, and himſelf is to be iudged of no man. God ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffereth not the church of Rome to erre. And euery one, that obeyeth not the decrees of the Romain Seat is an Heretick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> ſaith alſo. <hi>Wee iudge and ordaine by generall decree, that he be deteſtably ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curſed, and remain alwaies gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before God, as a breaker of the catholike faith, whoſoeuer shall ſuffer to be violat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, or be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeue that there ought to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated
<pb facs="tcp:10066:28"/>
in any point, the ſenſure of the decrees either of the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs or of the Bishops, or of any heerafter the mightie Popes of Roome. All the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the apoſtolick ſeat are ſo to bee eſteemed, as confirmed by the diuine voice of Peeter him ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With lowd voice</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth) <hi>I feare not to pronounce that whoſoeuer shalbe found, not indifferently to receiue and allow all the decrees of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers, which are intituled among vs by the names of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, hee is therby approoued ſuch a one, as dooth not profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably and effectually to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:28"/>
keepe or beleeue either the Catholick &amp; apoſtolick faith, or els the foure holy Goſpels. For, whoſoeuer dooth againſt her which is the mother of faith: dooth indeed breake and violate the faith. And albeit the Fathers of the Apoſtolick ſeate, ſome times bee not good: yet they are alwaies preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be good. The Pope ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth adultrye or murder, but he may not be ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſed. It were apoint of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge to diſpute of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes dooings: whoſe wicked acts are excuſed, as the murders of Sampſon, the robberies of the Hebrues and the adultery of
<pb facs="tcp:10066:29"/>
Iacob. Yea, alſo if one of the Clergie doo imbrace a woman, let it be ſaid that hee dooth it to bleſſe her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let no man think that I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed any of all theſe things. For I haue in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect reſited the very woords of the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, which I am able to ſhew in their owne Books if any man ſhall require it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Pope alone</hi> (ſay they) <hi>hath all the dignities &amp; all the power which all the Patriarcks haue had. His authoritie is greater then the authoritie of the ſaintes: becauſe whom he confirmeth, no man may diſable the ſame. He hath bothe the ſwordes. He is not to be called to account by any man, no, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be called an heretick. Hee alone appealeth from all
<pb facs="tcp:10066:29"/>
men to God him ſelf, becauſe he is the Vicar or deputie of Chriſte, and hath fulnes of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer from God. He may ſpare whom he luſt. To him alone and to none els: it is lawful to take a way from one and giue to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All the whole world is the dioceſse of the Pope: and the Pope is the ordinary of all men, hauing fulnes of power in things ſpirituall and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall. For he is Lord of Lords, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the right of the King of Kings ouer his ſubiects. He is all things and aboue all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And it is requiſit vnder pain of damnation to be ſubiect to the Bishop of Roome. For
<pb facs="tcp:10066:30"/>
God and the Pope haue bothe one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtory. Alſo, the pope is ſaid to haue an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly power and authority, and therfore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the nature of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by turning the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of one thing into an other. And of nothing he can make ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And the ſentence that is of no force: he can make it of ſome value. Becauſe in thoſe things that he liketh: his will ſtandeth for reaſon. And no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſay vnto him, why dooſt thou thus? For he may diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with all lawes, and of iniurye make Iuſtice, by correcting of lawes and chaunging of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hetherto haue ye heard the mouth ſpeaking great things, worthy truely to
<pb facs="tcp:10066:30"/>
be ſtopped vp with the Turds of the De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uil. But thus the Rat is bewrayed by ſhewing of her ſelf.</p>
               <p>And while he thus did ſhite foorth theſe moſte filthy Turds in the middeſt of the Church: yet ſtil he would needs ſéem to ſpeak on the behalf of the higheſt, whoſe Vicar he boſteth him ſelf to be on earth. <hi>VVho</hi> (as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaieth) <hi>dooth think that hee may chaunge bothe the times and the lawes.</hi> In very trueth, no man can or ought to chaunge the ordinances of God. Therfore Antichriſte ſhall think that he may chaunge them. <hi>Er wirds whaenem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Ierom</hi> noteth vpon theſe wordꝭ of <hi>Daniel,</hi> that Antichriſte ſhall make ſubiect vnder his power, the whole Reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion of Chriſte, Wherin we haue ſéen the Popes to haue doon what they luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them ſelues. But becauſe all times doo bring foorth faithful Preachers of Chriſte, <hi>Enoches</hi> and <hi>Eliaſes,</hi> who doo withſtand ſuch abhominations: therfore <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith very wel, <hi>that hee made war againſt the Saints, and preuailed ouer them.</hi> Of which war, becauſe I haue ſpoken before, when I expounded the woords of Chriſte our Lord: there is
<pb facs="tcp:10066:31"/>
no néed héer to make repetition again.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the godly, vppon whoſe ſhoulders this burden and care doth teſt, might demaund, how long time this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaſt ſhould rage, and waſte the kingdome of Chriſte, and blaſpheme the name of the eternall God: <hi>Daniel</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth this thing and ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The end of the Popes kingdome.</note>
                  <hi>They shalbe deliuered into his hands, vntil a time and times, and half a time.</hi> In whiche dark kinde of ſpeaking, he ſéemeth to ſignifie nothing elſe, but that the Saints muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly abide in that fight, whether the time, that they muſt fight in, be long or ſhort. For no certain determinate time is declared, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none muſt be looked for.</p>
               <p>Moſte men haue vnderſtanded, by a <hi>time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">For a time / times / and half a time.</note> 
                  <hi>times and half a time,</hi> one, yéere, ij. yéeres and half a yéere, in which Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte ſhould rain, and then afterward ſhould be quite aboliſhed. But the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel is repugnant to that interpretation, which conſtantly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the day of iudgement is kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto no man. And <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo in the ſelf ſame chapter ſaith, that the beaſt ſhall rage, vntil the ſeats be prepared, that is euen vntil the day of iudgement.
<pb facs="tcp:10066:31"/>
And that he ſhall then be thrown down hedlong in to the déep pit of Hel, and alſo that the faithful ſhalbe deliuered and glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rified, who haue for Chriſtes cauſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained all kindes of puniſhments.</p>
               <p>Verily <hi>Paule</hi> agréeing with <hi>Daniel: VVhom our Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>shall put away with the brightneſſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> But who can certainly declare vnto vs the time of Chriſtes comming, that is, the day of Iudgement? But hée, which ſhall ſay, that Antichriſte ſhall reign iij. yéeres and a half, and ſtraight wayes after be aboliſhed, may ſeeme to declare it plainly. For the end of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes kingdome, is the very laſt day of the finall Iudgement.</p>
               <p>Therfore by that dark kinde of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, no time certain is appointed. But rather the godly are admoniſhed, of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and long ſuffering, and that we ſhould not ouer curiouſly ſéeke out the very moment of this time, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it vnto Chriſte, who ſaieth in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place vnto his Diſciples. <hi>It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not to you, to knowe the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and moments of times, which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath reſerued vnto him ſelf. But vvatch ye, that when your Lord shall
<pb facs="tcp:10066:32"/>
come, he may finde you vvaking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe things <hi>Daniel</hi> moſte plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully witneſſeth, that the world ſhalbe at an end, and that the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhall certainly come, and throwe down Antichriſte in to Hel.</p>
               <p>Vpon which treatiſe, Chriſt our Lord hath ſet foorth a large Commentary and an expoſition, by the hands of <hi>Iohn,</hi> his Apoſtle in the xix. and xx. chapters of the <hi>Apocalips,</hi> the which I leaue vnto your diligence to be ſerched out, and for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake: I doo not ouer buſily ſift out this matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.</note>And now (I ſuppoſe) it appéereth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, by the moſte cleere doctrine of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte our Lord, and alſo by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident ſayings of the moſte holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God, and by the plain interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the moſte ſelect and choſen A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſte. Finally the manifeſt compariſon of the things them ſelues, which partely the Hiſtories doo teſtifie, to haue béen doon a long time agoe, and partly we ſée them dayly come to paſſe before oure eyes, that the Prophecyes of the laſt time are now all ready fulfilled, and that therfore the day of our Lord is at hand, and our redemption approcheth
<pb facs="tcp:10066:32"/>
néere.</p>
               <p>Wherby (I think) you all doo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that your duties require you, to admoniſh, to exhorte, and inſtantly to call vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and vrge the faithful, to watch and lift vp their heads, ſhaking away all drowſines. And that they looke for none other ſignes, nor other times: but to beleeue the Goſpel, the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the very things them ſelues apparent before the eyes of all men, and alſo that they wait not for any other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte to come, but to take now good héed to them ſelues, of him, that is now preſently reigning and troubling all things, &amp; to flée vnto Chriſte Ieſus, who is the fulnes of the faithful, and in him to ſéek all things pertaining to our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to depend wholy vppon his mouth, and vppon his help, to haue reſpect vnto him alone, to depart from all vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to liue godly and honeſtly, and moſte chéefly to beware of vngodly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, and careles negligence, and alſo of drunkenneſſe bothe ſpirituall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, that when the Iudge our Lord Ieſus Chriſte ſhall appéere in the clouds of Heauen with great power and glory,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:33"/>
we may ioyfully be taken vp in to the aire to meet him, and ſo alwaies liue with our Lord. To whom be glory for euer.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:10066:33"/>
               <head>¶<hi>THE SECOND</hi> Sermon of Henry Bullinger, <hi>teaching by the woords of the</hi> Apoſtle. <hi>2. Timothe 3.</hi> after what ſorte <hi>the godly may auoid the harms of</hi> the moſte perillous daungers in this our laſt age.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight notable is</hi> the place of the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> which in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter epiſtle to <hi>Timothe,</hi> and the third Chapter is woord by woord after this ſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But perſeuer thou in thoſe things, which thou haſt learned, and vvhich haue been committed vnto thee, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vvhom thou haſt learned them, and for that alſo thou haſt knowen ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures from a childe, vvhich are able to make thee vviſe vnto ſaluation through faith in Chriſte Ieſu. For all Scriptures giuen by inſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: are profitable to teach, to reprooue, to amend to inſtruct in rightuouſneſſe, that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God may be perfet, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parad
<pb facs="tcp:10066:34"/>
to all good vvorks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſet foorth euen to our eyes</note>The bountiful goodnes of God, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mankinde ſhineth foorth in many things, but moſte chéefly in that, that he hath ſo meaſured the doctrin of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, which he committed to the world, by moſte excellent men, that it is agréea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble not onely to the ſame time, in which it was firſt ſet foorth by the prophets and Apoſtles: but vnto vs alſo, vppon whom the ends of the worlde are come. And truely all the moſte holy cumpany of the Prophets and Apoſtles with one conſent doo teſtifie, that the laſt times ſhalbe of all other moſte perillus. They doo moſte diligently and copiouſly, not onely deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe thoſe daungers: but alſo ſet them foorth before our eyes to be ſeene, to that end (no dout) that the godly ſhould not be entangled and periſh in euil and in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and drift of the matter.</note>Of that number is <hi>Paule</hi> the veſſel of election, who at this preſent, procéeding in moſte godly order, dooth firſt of all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diligently ſhowe foorth the daungers of this our laſt age. Afterward hée de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth a remedy, wherby the godly may eſcape the harmes therof. The thing is not onely elegant, notable and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome:
<pb facs="tcp:10066:34"/>
but alſo very neceſſary, moſte chée<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fly for vs and our time.</p>
               <p>Therfore haue I choſen this place, to entreat of now, before you (ye honorable fathers and bretheren moſte déerly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in our Lord) that beeing inſtructed with the doctrin of the Apoſtles: we may through the ſpirite of God, be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened in true godlineſſe, and he able to deliuer out of daungers, the flock of our Lord committed to our charge, the Lord bleſſing our labours. Our Lord aſſiſt vs with his grace, and direct vs alwaies in the way of ſaluation.</p>
               <p>But,<note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the euil acts &amp; daungers recited in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> like as the Phiſitions in their books doo moſte diligently deſcribe euen ſuch diſeaſes, as are moſte filthy, not to the intent to praiſe and commend them, or els allow them: but to th'nd they may be exactly knowne, and the more perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cured: ſo the Scripture in this preſent place, &amp; infinite others, doth moſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly reherſe miſcheuous deeds euen ſuch as are to be abhorred, and not to be named without ſir reuerence, not to the intent to teach and commend the ſame: but to the end wee might knowe them the better, &amp; iudge therof, not according to the fleſh: but according to the ſpirite of
<pb facs="tcp:10066:35"/>
God, and alſo that we might warely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid them. And more ouer apparently beholding, thoſe things to be fulfilled in the world, which the holy Prophets of God and the Apoſtles of Chriſte haue foretolde ſhould come to paſſe, we might vnderſtand, that thoſe times are now at hand corrupted and perillous, and for that cauſe ſhould pray the more erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and watch the more diligently.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle therfore about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter, a litle before the words that I haue reſited, dooth reherſe in a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g beadroll, diuers wicked acts and wicked men, And ſaith that all ages, all kindes, and all degrees of men in this our laſt time, ſhall be moſte corrupt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The diſcrp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the manners or men of the laſt age.</note>
                  <hi>This knovve thou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that in the laſt daies shall come moſte hard and perillous times. For men shalbe loouers of them ſelues, ſtanding greatly in their ovvne conceits, and ſeeking for their owne gaine, louers of their owne gaine, louers of money, ſcraping the ſame by hook and by crooke, &amp; not refraining from very ſacriledge, nor from moſte filthy Simony. Men shalbe very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful, puffed vp, proude, and vain glorious, alſo blaſphemers, moſte chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly
<pb facs="tcp:10066:35"/>
againſt God, ſecondly againſt holy men and againſt the trueth it felt, and againſt holy things. They shalbe diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to their Fathers, to their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to their magiſtrats, to their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to their teachers, beeing not onely vnthankful to God and to men: but alſo requiting good turnes vvith euil. They shalbe vvicked men, ſuch as haue no fear nor reuerence, and ſuch as impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly run hedlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto all kind of miſcheuoꝰ acts. They shalbe Aſtorgoi, vvithout any harty and feruent chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vvithout any zelus remorſe of loue, godlines, and humanitie, not louing ſomuch as thoſe that be neer vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Fathers, mothers, Children, VViues and kinſfolkes. But bitter, cruel, and vngentle, endued vtterly vvith vvilde and vnciuil manners, vvho alſo haue not the common ſence and remorſe of nature, meaſuring all things by affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by couetouſnes, by ambition, and greedy deſire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They shalbe vnmindeful of their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, of their faith, of their bargaines, and of their promiſes, beeing vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and moſte vain, and vtterly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and moſte light perſons, finally,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:36"/>
back biters and ſlanderers, ſcoffers and mockers of holy, good &amp; honeſt thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, peruerting alſo things vvel ſpoken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a peruerſt meaning, and vvreſting things after their levvd affections, that are ſingly and plainly vttered. They shalbe vvanton and outragious, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the apparel of their bodies, in buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dings, in garments, in meat and drink, filthy glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, drounckerds whoremon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers, adulterers, and Sodomits, proud Pecoks, nice and folish Phrigians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They shalbe moreouer Anemeroi, vngentle, vnciuil, rude, barbarous, and euen vvilde men,</hi> rowe wild vnd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fihiſch lijt. <hi>&amp; therfore Aphilagathoj ſuch as greatly regard not or looue not good and honeſt men, neither delight in their company. For, as they abhorre the beſt things and accuſtome them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to the vvorſt: ſo they cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide a faithful Counceller. Therfore they shall betray theſe men, that looue trueth and godlines. They shall doo no thing ſincerely and vncorruptly, but shall intangle all things vvith practiſes (as they call them) vvith crafty fetches and traitorly ſuttleties. Moreouer they
<pb facs="tcp:10066:36"/>
shalbe heddy and vvilful, dooing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the rule of reaſon and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but all things rashly ſtoutly, and obſtinately. For they shalbe of a minde altogither proud, puffed vp and ſvvelling. They shall looue their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, more then God him ſelf and god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly things. For they shall conuert the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry religion in to gaine, to the intent they may haue to beſtovve vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certes, thou maiſt ſée very many, that more hartily delight in Tauernes then in Temples, doo more eſtéeme the furniſhed daintie, yea drunken feaſts, then eccleſiaſticall preachings ſober and ful of the ſpirite of God. For the matter is now come to this point, that moſte men haue in déede an outward ſhewe and reſemblance of godlineſſe, and will be called moſte holy, moſte ſpirituall, moſte catholike, moſte right belonging, and very good Chriſtians, but yet in the mean ſeaſon they lack the vertue and power of godlines and true Religion, and are moſte vaine Hipocrites and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſemblers, men without all religion and humanitie, abominable and execrable.</p>
               <p>And hitherto hath the Apoſtle decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:10066:37"/>
theſe things concerning the corrupt men, that ſhalbe in the laſt time, and the naughty conditions of all kindes, of all ages, and of all degrées.</p>
               <p>But haue not the Prophets, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf, the Lord of Prophets, foreſhewed theſe things alſo before hand? For in the Goſpel (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Prophets) he ſpeaking moſte manifeſtly ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note>
                  <hi>But vvhen the Sonne of man shall come, shall he finde faith vppon the Earth?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> And again. <hi>Iniquitie shall vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abound, and the looue of many shall abate.</hi> And yet again moſte many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As were the daies of Noe</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>ſo shall be alſo the comming of the ſonne of man. For as they were in the daies before the flud, eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, marying and maried, euen vnto the day when Noe entred into the Arke, and knewe of nothing, vntill the Flud came and tooke them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waiy: ſo shalbe the comming of the Sonne of man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>In like manner alſo, as it happened in the daies of Loth, they did eat, drink, bie, ſel, plant, and build. But what day as Loth went foorth
<pb facs="tcp:10066:37"/>
from the Sodomits, it rained fire and brimſtone from Heauen, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all, ſo shalbe alſo the day in vvhich the Sonne of man sbalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherfore there is no cauſe, to ſhew forth in many woords, what kinde of men they were in the daies of <hi>Noe</hi> and <hi>Loth,</hi> ſeeing our Lord him ſelf hath moſt plentifully declared the ſame vnto vs, namely, that they were men altogither carnall, vtterly deſpiſing diuine and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, ſéeking nothing but carnall matters, ſo that they might ſéem to dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate or be turned in to certain brute and wilde beaſtes. But who can deny, that ſuch are at this day the greateſt parte of the common people, and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and rulers, and almoſte all wiſe men? Beholde what Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doo, and alſo the ſpiritual fathers, like wiſe the learned and excellent men in the world. Harken what the common people talketh of Religion, of rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of honeſtie, and of the hope of the world to come. You ſhalbe forced to cry out with the Prophet and ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is none righteous no not one.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>There is none that hath vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.
<pb facs="tcp:10066:38"/>
There is none that ſeeketh after God. All are turned aſide, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnprofitable. There is none that dooth good, no not one. Their throte is an open Sepulchre, they haue vſed their tungs vnto diſceit, and the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Aſps is vnder their lips, whoſe mouth is ful of curſſing and bitternes, their feet are ſwift to shed blood. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and wretchedneſſe is in their vvaies, and they haue not knowen the vvay of peace. There is no feare of God before their eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle procedeth to recken vp greater daungers, whiche ſpring out of corrupt men, and out of their corrupt and wicked doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the corrupt doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine of the laſt age.</note>For he ſaith, there ſhall be in the Church. <hi>Some deceiuers, flattering, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and crafty, that vvil enter into no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houſes, and bring vvomen into bondage, vvhich women are led with diuers luſts.</hi> He addeth. <hi>That their doctrine shal finde no Hauen, nor haue any end, and that no mans conſcience can therby be prepared or made quiet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to the intent they might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be knowen when they come: he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them to the Soothſayers of <hi>Egipt,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:38"/>
who with ther ſpeaking, with their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked practiſes, Sorceries and moſte craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty legerdemain: wrought meanes before <hi>Pharao</hi> the King of Egipt, that he ſhuld not let go the Iſraellits y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of God, to doo honour to their God. And Chriſte our Lord making mention of the very ſame deceiuers, ſaith in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There shall ariſe falſe Chriſtes &amp; falſe Prophets, vvho shall vvork great mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and great vvunders, ſo that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry elect, if it vvere poſſible, shoulde be brought in to error. Beholde, I haue tolde you before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is it néedful for me, to make plain and with large diſcourſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue how theſe things alredy haue béen abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly fulfilled long time agoe, and in certain hundred yéeres togither. A thouſand examples and teſtimonies maiſt thou finde in the Temples of the Papiſts, in their Chappels, in their Schooles, in their Halles, in their Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in their Abbies and religious hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>To the great weight of the daungers of this laſt age,<note place="margin">Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the laſt age.</note> are now added alſo euen moſte cruell perſecutions of the trueth, and of the Saints, which the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:10066:39"/>
hath foreſhewed ſhould come to paſſe.</p>
               <p>Moreouer he ſaith, that the wicked ſhould with fortunate ſucceſſe, proſper, and go forward, but contrary wiſe that the Godly ſhould be oppreſſed with all kinde of calamities, the whiche thing ſhould blinde very many, and kéep them in error. The very ſame alſo did our Lord Ieſus foretel of in the Goſpel. And <hi>Daniel</hi> diſputing of Antichriſte and his kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel. 8. and 11.</note>
                  <hi>And he shall proſper</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and shall vvork, and ſlay the ſtrong ones, and the people of the Saints, according to his ovvn vvil, and falshod shall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his hands.</hi> Alſo. <hi>The teachers of the people shall inſtruct many, and shall be ouerthrovvne through the Svvord, through fire, through banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and extortion, euen vntil the laſt time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that euen theſe things alſo are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed: it is plentifully witneſſed by the Hiſtories of certain hundred yéeres laſt paſt. <hi>England</hi> alſo at this day yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding foorth abundant ſtore of Martirs, dooth teſtify the ſame. <hi>Fraunce</hi> dooth wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe it. <hi>Italy</hi> &amp; <hi>Germany</hi> doo record it.</p>
               <p>And theſe things hetherto the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb facs="tcp:10066:39"/>
of Chriſte hath ſpoken, touching the great perils of the laſt age. All which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to appertain vnto vs moſte chéefly and to our times, he, that as yet ſeeth it not: dooth ſee no thing at all. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in knowing theſe diſeaſes and diſcerning them with right iudgement, although it be of no ſmall importaunce: neuertheleſſe a more wholeſome frute procedeth vnto vs by the diligent conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the medicine, faithfully mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto vs by the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>But what medicine dooth the Apoſtle bring foorth and miniſter, by help wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe diſeaſes are to be cured, and the great dangers made free from hurtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?<note place="margin">The medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine or cure of theſe miſcheefs.</note> 
                  <hi>And theſe men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>auoid thou.</hi> It is ſhort councel, and a medicine nothing curious, but yet of meruelous force. But whom dooth he meane, while he ſaith. <hi>And theſe men?</hi> Forſooth wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men paſt grace, enemies of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and moſte chéefly ſuttle Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, deceiuers, bloody percecutors, falſe Prophets, and ſuch as are drunken with the proſperitie, happines and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world.</p>
               <p>Theſe (I ſay) and all their partakers and confederates auoid thou. The
<pb facs="tcp:10066:40"/>
which thing is aſmuch in effect, as if he had ſaid. Such wicked men and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, thou ſhalt deteſt as an hainous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not feare them, thou ſhalt not eſtéeme them, thou ſhalt not allow them nor folow them, thou ſhalt nothing at all beléeue them. No doo not play with them, nor confer with them. Finally, thou ſhalt turn from them perpetually with erneſt endeuour, and with a whole bolde and a ſtout minde. For the Lord alſo hath ſaid in the Goſpel. <hi>Beleue them not,</hi> or folow not, nor imitate the falſe Prophet. But, thou wilt obiect, that this is a hard matter to performe. But vnto God, and to him that beleeueth: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is impoſſible or hard.</p>
               <p>Iohn the Apoſtle crieth out ſaying. <hi>He is greater,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4. and 5.</note> 
                  <hi>that is in you, then he, vvhich is in the vvorld.</hi> And againe. <hi>This is the victory that ouercommeth the vvorld, euen your faith.</hi> For our Lord firſt cryed out in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel. <hi>Beholde I am vvith you euen vnto the vvorlds end.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 28. Iohn. 1. and 14. &amp;c. Luke. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>In the vvorld ye haue affliction. But be of good cheere, I haue ouercom the vvorld. One here shall not perish from your head. I vvil giue to you my
<pb facs="tcp:10066:40"/>
ſpirite the comforter.</hi> And other ſuch like ſayings, which are read in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, the Apoſtle ſheweth a very commodious way, how we may be able to avoid theſe corrupt men, and all corruptions in Religion, and alſo to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew thoſe perillous daungers, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if with a certain holy erneſtnes we cleue vnto the example of the Apoſtle, and taking faſt holde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the canonicall Scriptures, doo not ſuffer our ſelues to be ſhaken of, or pulled away one heres bredth from the ſame. And the Apoſtle him ſelf commendeth vnto vs the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of an Apoſtle ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt ſeene the experience of my doctrin, fashion of liuing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">we muſt not depart from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> 
                  <hi>and my purpoſe alſo, namely in teaching, in ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp; in all my office, what I regarde in theſe things, verily the glory of God and ſaluation of ſoules. Finally thou knoweſt vvhat my faith hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, my long ſuffering, my conſtancy and my patience in perſecutions. Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv thou theſe things, declining no vvhit from the example of Chriſte and of me.</hi> For our Lord ſaid alſo in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:41"/>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note>
                  <hi>I am the light of the vvorld. He that foloweth me, walketh not in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but hath the light of life.</hi> And the Apoſtle to the Corinthians. <hi>Be ye folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of mee as I folowe Chriſte.</hi> But, becauſe the men of this laſt age, doo not much eſteeme the example of Chriſte and of his Apoſtles, but doo more regard the examples of Fathers (I knowe not of what ſorte) and of moſte filthy Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ks, that is therfore the cauſe, why there are ſo many ſects, and that ſo many wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der about, and grope like blinde men, not knowing what or whom to folowe, or what they may teach. Wherfore, as many of vs as deſire to be ſaued: let vs kéep our ſelues within the bonds of the example of Chriſte and of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e muſt continue in the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les doctrin.</note>Now touching the Apoſtles doctrine, we are admoniſhed by the Apoſtle: Firſt that we muſt continew in the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles doctrine. Afterward, he ſheweth the cauſes, why euery godly man ought to continue in that kinde of doctrine. For he pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth plainly and techeth with great power, he ſaith. <hi>But tary thou, or continevv thou ſtedfaſtly.</hi> As if hée ſhould haue ſaid. How ſoeuer the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:10066:41"/>
and deceiued, go foreward in their errors, houſoeuer graet numbers of men departing from the plainnes and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Apoſtles, doo folowe corrupt doctrin and thoſe <hi>Egiptian</hi> Sophiſters: yet neuertheleſſe, perſeuer and continue ſtil thou &amp; all others, that couet to pleaſe God, and to abtain true ſaluation. In what things I pray you ſhall they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew?</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle addeth it. <hi>In thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vvhich thou haſt learned, and vvhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch haue ben committed vnto thee.</hi> But Timothe had learned the Scriptures, and out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy goſpel, as ſtraight way the Apoſtle wil expound him ſelf.</p>
               <p>And this was that precious pledge which was committed vnto him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the godly muſt perſeuer and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the Scriptures and in the doctrin of the Goſpel. So ſhall it come to paſſe, that they ſhall not be a pray to the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and to the moſt wicked men of this laſt age.<note place="margin">what was committe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vnto Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</note> Neither muſt we think (as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fooliſh men doo fain) that vnwritten Traditions were committed vnto Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe, as though the Apoſtle had ment, that without traditions, the Scriptures ſuffiſe not vnto godlineſſe, or that he had
<pb facs="tcp:10066:42"/>
taught one thing by woord of mouth: and another thing in writing. For by and by the Apoſtle him ſelf wil declare, that the Scriptures are moſte ful, and moſte abſolute, ſuch as are able throughly to faſhion and make perfect the worſhipper of God. The Apoſtle els where affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth very intirely,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.</note> that his doings agrée in one ſorte all alike, and that he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth like doctrin in all Churches. He ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth alſo, that he and his diſiples walke all one way, and béeing all led by one ſpirit, doo all things with humilitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 3.</note>Again to the Corinthians. <hi>VVee vvrite</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>none other things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you then vvhich ye read, and vvhich alſo ye knovve. Yea and ſo I truſt, that ye shall knovve vnto the end</hi> And again.<note place="margin">4. Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>As vve are in vvords by letters, vvhen vve are abſent: ſuch are vve in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed alſo, vvhen we are preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is openly apparant that thoſe things, whiche thoſe men recken vp a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong the vnwritten verities, affirming the ſame to be receiued from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, euen (as if were) from hand to hand, are ſo diſagreing with thoſe things which are contained in the writings of the Apoſtles: that they are euen directly
<pb facs="tcp:10066:42"/>
repugnant and contrary.</p>
               <p>Of which kinde are thoſe matters, which they ſtuf in, conſerning the vſe of Images in the Church, conſerning the Maſſe, conſerning ſingle life and Munc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery, and infinit other ſuch ingling de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits. Where alſo euen that is diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be noted, that he ſaid not. <hi>Tary thou in thoſe things which thou shalt learn yet heerafter. But, tary thou in thoſe hings vvhich thou haſt learned.</hi> To vs therfore, partain not thoſe things, which wretched men after certain hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yéeres, haue learned of Fathers (ſuch as indéed may be called ſtepfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) and of lewd and ſuperſtitious Munks.</p>
               <p>It foloweth now, why we ought to cleue onely to this doctrin.<note place="margin">Why wee ought to cleue only to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures.</note> Indéed many reaſons may be alleaged, but among ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny theſe are the chéefeſt. Firſt, <hi>Knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of vvhom thou haſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them.</hi> Truely it is much to be reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of what maiſters or teachers we learne any thing. For the doctrin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth authoritie from the teachers, or author therof. It is thought that from the more excellent, cunning and holy men, proceedeth ſome excellent learned
<pb facs="tcp:10066:43"/>
and holy thing.</p>
               <p>Verily, from men procéed humaine things, and from God procéed godly and deuine things. But of whom had Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe learned? or from whom came the doctrin receiued by Timothe? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the moſt holy Apoſtle, and moſt ſelect inſtructment of God. Therfore, not the man <hi>Paule,</hi> but rather the Spirit of Chriſte (inſpiring <hi>Paule</hi>) hath purchaſed authoritie vnto the doctrine. Therefore Timothe knewe, and al the faithful al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo at this day knowe, that the doctrine of the Apoſtles ſprang not from men: but from our Lord God him ſelf, and that therfore we ought to beléeue the ſame, and inſeperably cleue vnto it. For our Lord him ſelf ſaith in his Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note>
                  <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, hee, that receiueth an Apoſtle, or vvhom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I shall ſend: receiueth me. And he that receiueth me: receiueth him that ſent me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> And again, ſpeaking of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. <hi>It is not you that ſpeak but it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſpirite of your father, that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> And again. <hi>He that is from aboue, is aboue all. He that procedeth of the Earth, is earthly, and ſpeaketh of the earth. He that commeth from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:43"/>
is aboue all, and what he hath ſeen and heard the ſame: he teſtifieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherfore in aſmuch as it appéereth, that the doctrin of the Apoſtle is heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; deuine: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good cauſe doo we beléeue, with good cauſe doo we inſeperably cleue to it. Neither did the Apoſtles without great reaſon ſay. <hi>therfore shalt thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in the apoſtles doctrin, which thou haſt receiued, becauſe thou dooſt ſurely knowe that thou haſt receiued and learned the ſame from Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But can we ſo ſay of the vnwritten traditions, and of the ordinances of man? No, by no meanes. Therfore, why ſhould we beleeeue them? why ſhould we receiue them? why ſhould we continew in them? Theſe things are due to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures only and alone. They are vtterly mad, that make humain things equall with deuine. But they are led by the Deuil, that prefer things humain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diuine, and thruſt downe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bace diuine things as though they were vncertain, doutful, vnperfect and darke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> the moſte notable King, and moſte excellent Prophet of God, crieth but againſt ſuch filthy and blaſphemous perſons, and pronounceth with moſte
<pb facs="tcp:10066:44"/>
true mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note>
                  <hi>The lawe of the Lord is a perfect law conuerting the ſoule. The teſtimonie of the Lord is true, giuing wiſdome to the litle ones. The ſtatutes of the Lord are right, and reioice the hart. The commaundement of the Lord is pure, and giueth light to the eyes. Thy word is a Lantern vnto my feet, and a light vnto my ſteps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore, the Apoſtles doctrine is grounded vppon the Scriptures or writings of the Prophets,<note place="margin">The Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les doctrine is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vppon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring witnes and ſaying. <hi>I was put a part to preach the Goſpel of GOD, vvhiche he promiſed afore by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in the holy Scriptures.</hi> But we knowe, that the ſame are therfore called holy, becauſe they are vttered by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſte. It foloweth therfore in the woords of the Apoſtle. <hi>And for that alſo thou haſt knowen the holy Scriptures from a childe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The holy fathers in olde time were w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to inſtruct their children out of the authenticall Booke of the lawe of God and of his Prophets. Therfore, becauſe Timothes mother was a Iew borne (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit his Father was a Gentil) he béeing
<pb facs="tcp:10066:44"/>
exerciſed in the ſcriptures from a childe, had accuſtomed him ſelf therunto.</p>
               <p>And when he heard the Apoſtle preache the Goſpel of Chriſte, hee vnderſtoode ſtraightway by the inſpiration of the ſpirit of God, and by conferring of the woords of <hi>Paule,</hi> with the woords of the Prophets, that the Apoſtles doctrine tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Chriſte, was taken out of the law and the Prophets, and confirmed by the teſtimonyes of the ſame. And for that cauſe he knew that he had not learned the faith of Chriſte, out of wandering ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and vain talks of the people: but out of the autenticall Booke, that is to ſay, out of the holy Scriptures, namely inſpired from God (as I haue already declared) and deuoutly taught and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, touching things moſte pure of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by none, but by ſuch as were moſte holy men. All other books that where out of the Canon and common vſe of the Church: are accounted vnder the name of prophane Books.</p>
               <p>But this is an effectuall reaſon, and ſuch a one as ought throughly to mooue the mindes of all men, that we muſt therfore beléeue the Apoſtles doctrin, and cleue only to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: becauſe it proceded
<pb facs="tcp:10066:45"/>
from God, and is confirmed by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall Scriptures, béeing moſte an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moſte holy of all other.</p>
               <p>What ſo euer booke of what ſo euer Authors thou ſhalt compare with theſe Books: thou ſhalt ſcarcely compare Lead or durt it ſelf, with moſte fine and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Golde. Moſte rightly therfore doo we beléeue that they of all men be moſte fooliſh, who either omitting the Apoſtles doctrin, and writings of the Prophets, turn aſide to the inuentions of man (as though there could be taught or contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe, more abſolute, more cléere, and more certain things, then in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) or elſe vtterly giue no credit at all vnto the Scriptures. The taunt which our Lord gaue to the vnbeléeuing diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, is right notable and woorthy of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall remembrance,<note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note> when he ſaid, <hi>O ye fooles and ſlovv of hart, to beleeue all thoſe things vvhich the Prophets haue ſpoken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is able to make a man wiſe vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>And now enſueth in the Apoſtle, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon no leſſe euident, why we ought only to beleue and ſtick faſt to the Apoſtles doctrin, and to the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they are able to make
<pb facs="tcp:10066:45"/>
thee wiſe vnto ſaluation, through faith in chriſte Ieſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Philoſophers haue diſputed much of true and falſe Wiſdome,<note place="margin">True wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> and haue ſo entangled them ſelues with their chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, that they ſcarcely vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them ſelues, and muche leſſe reaped any frute of their diſputations. <hi>Paule</hi> dooth ſimply and truely deriue true Wiſdome out of the Scriptures of God, and out of the Apoſtles doctrine.</p>
               <p>For God (béeing moſte excellent wiſe) dooth very often in his woord call his commaundements and the doctrine (ſet foorth in his lawe, and by the Prophets) true Wiſdome. And <hi>Moyſes</hi> béeing el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then thoſe men, whom the <hi>Greti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> call moſte ancient, namely <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Heſiodus,</hi> and the Battel of <hi>Troy,</hi> and alſo béeing much more excellent then <hi>Hercules, Muſeus, Linus, Orphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Mercurius, Apollo,</hi> and the other Gods of the Gentiles, or then euen the holy Soothſayers: elder alſo then the wiſe men of <hi>Greece.</hi> Much more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent then <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> dooth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſay in Deuteronomy.<note place="margin">Deu. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>You shall keep and doo the commaundements of the Lord for this is your wiſdome and
<pb facs="tcp:10066:46"/>
vnderſtanding in the ſight of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which shall hear all theſe ordinan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and shall ſay. This people only is wiſe and hath vnderſtanding, a famous Nation.</hi> But the Apoſtles alſo at this preſent dooth ſhew, that ſaluation is the end and alſo the frute of true wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying. <hi>VVhich are able to make thee wiſe vnto ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, without the true ſaluation of man, what ſhall auaile (I pray you) the empty name and vain title of wiſedome? Wiſdome is the knoweledge of things diuine and humain, and moſte chéefely of thoſe things, by which we may knowe the higheſt good euen God him ſelf, and therwithall to be ioyned togither with Chriſte. The which indeed is true ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſednes and the higheſt felicitie. And now I omit to rehearſe, how that out of this knowledge of God, ſpringeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and the looue and exerciſe of true vertue, and of all deeds that are truely good.</p>
               <p>But the Scripture and doctrine of the Apoſtles, abundantly ſuffiſeth to giue this Wiſdome and true ſaluation. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it becommeth vs, to content our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with the ſame. Yea, it is expedient
<pb facs="tcp:10066:46"/>
for vs, to beſtowe all our life and all our labour vppon thoſe holy books, to depend wholly vppon them, to direct all our ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and all our waies by the ſame, as by a moſte infallible and moſte ſure l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de Starre, to run and flée wholy vnto them, as to a moſte ſafe Sanctuary. For, <hi>Dauid</hi> cryeth out and witneſſeth ſaying</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man that delighteth in the lawe of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and erneſtly ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieth in the ſame, bothe day and night.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 11.</note> For the Lord ſayeth alſo in the Goſpel. <hi>Bleſſed are they that hear the woord of God and keepe the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in deed this ſhalbe the onely and ſafeſt way, to eſcape all perils of al times and all deceits and legerdemain, yea, euen the moſte ſharp and cruel of this our laſt age. But, becauſe ſaluation might be hoped for by this heauenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, and alſo by the reading and bare knoweledge of the holy Scriptures, or els by the merits of the vertues, whiche we haue learned out of the Scriptures, therfore in déed very godly and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely he addeth and ſayth.<note place="margin">Saluation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by faith in Chriſte.</note> 
                  <hi>Through faith in Chriſte Ieſu.</hi> Therfore ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is learned out of the Scriptures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it conſiſteth in Chriſte alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10066:47"/>And Chriſte, who is the bread of life, the ſaluation and fulnes of the Saints, dooth onely and alone giue true ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But true faith béeing inſtructed by the ſpirite of God, and by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, receiueth the ſame.</p>
               <p>Saluation therfore is to be attributed vnto faith, &amp; not to any other thing but yet not to euery faith: but only vnto the ſame that commeth vnto vs by the grace and benefit of the holy ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we lerne out of the Scriptures, the true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, &amp; which extendeth and is ſtaied vpon the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>only ſonne of God, who is our onely moſte abſolute, moſt aſſured and eternal righteouſnes, redemption, ſatiſfaction, ſanctification, life and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But,<note place="margin">The end &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ft of the Scriptures</note> as ſoon as the Apoſtle hath expounded theſe things very elegantly and plainly he ſheweth, what is the end and mark, to the which we muſt direct all the reading of the holy Scriptures, that is to ſay, to learn faith, euen faith in Chriſte, who is our life and ſaluation.</p>
               <p>To that very end did <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſtretch foorth all his whole ſtory of the Goſpel, while (concluding the ſame) he ſayeth. <hi>Theſe things are written, to the intent ye might beleeue, that Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:10066:47"/>
is Chriſte the ſonne of God, and that beleeuing: yee might haue life in his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſequently, the Apoſtle procéedeth with a ſhort praiſe,<note place="margin">The praiſe of holy Scripture.</note> but yet notable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending many thinges, and therfore worthy to be remembered, to commend vnto vs the Canonicall Scriptures, not ſomuch, to prooue them to ſuffiſe to the learning and attaynment of ſaluation, as with them to glue faſt togither the mindes of all men, while we all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that there remaineth vtterly no whit of ſound profitable, wholeſome and neceſſary doctrin, but the ſame is handled and taught moſte perfectly in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Therfore <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth and ſayeth. <hi>All Scriptures giuen by inſpiration of God, are profitable, to teach. &amp;c.</hi> And hée plainly ſayeth, <hi>All Scriptures.</hi> For if thou ſhalt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently read and conſider euery of the Bookes of holy Scripture (bée they neuer ſo ſhort) thou ſhalt finde in euery of them all theſe things that are héer recited, that is to ſay, that euery one of them is able to teach, to reprooue, to amend, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. But very ſkilfully he addeth, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opneuſtos,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:48"/>
giuen by the inſpiration of God</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the inſpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of God.</note>For there be extant euery where au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and bookes innumerable, béeing not inſpired of God, but ſet foorth by the wil of man: with the which wee haue héer nothing to doo. For the holy bookes haue this thing proper and pecul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar to them ſelues alone, namely that they be giuen by inſpiration of God, as I haue all ready ſaid a little before. And <hi>Peter</hi> alſo the Apoſtle teſtifieth ſaying. <hi>No prophecy of the Scriptures hath any priuat interpretation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Peter. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Scripture came neuer by the wil of man: but holy men of God, ſpake as they were mooued by the holy Ghoſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this point are all our Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or holy Books, diſcerned from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy and prophane books of all other wiſe men. And it is a principle of our religion and of our faith, namely that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are giuen by the Inſpiration of God. Wherby it commeth to paſſe, that this ſaying is very often read in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord. Thus ſaith the Lord god of hoſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſte truely therfore <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he was a Iew, ſpeaking of the Books
<pb facs="tcp:10066:48"/>
of the olde Teſtament, againſt <hi>Appio Alexandrinus</hi> in his firſt Booke ſayeth thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee haue no infinit number of Bookes amongſt vs, diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing and repugnaunt one to another: but only xxij. books, wherin is regeſtred all the whole time to the whiche we iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly giue credit. For it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by our dooings, how we beleeue our owne writings. For in all theſe many hundred yeeres paſt, no man hath preſumed either to adde, or to take away, or to chaunge any thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, it is implanted in to all the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, euen from their cradles, to talke of theſe holy decrees, and ſtedfaſtly to dwel in them, and alſo, if need require, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to dye for the ſame. With good cauſe, therfore doo wée beléeue our books,
<pb facs="tcp:10066:49"/>
of the two Teſtaments, without gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying and curious ſearch, or buſie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry. It ſuffiſeth whatſoeuer the holy Scriptures ſhall ſay vnto vs, if we right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtand the ſame. For néed wée muſt beléeue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The profit of the holy Sciptures.</note>But, now let vs heare to what vſes the holy Scripture is profitable. The Apoſtle recoueth vp iiij. kindes, and vnder them he comprehendeth all other the like. For it is moſte certain, that there is nothing wanting in the holy Scriptures, namely, whatſoeuer it bée, that ſéemeth to appertain to moſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect wiſdome and doctrine. And firſt he ſaith, <hi>That the Scripture giuen by the inſpiration of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth.</note> 
                  <hi>is profitable to teach.</hi> For indeed, to vnderſtand the true doctrine and wiſdome, it behooueth vs firſt of all to haue the right knowledge of things, to the intent we may perceiue what and of what kinde euery thing is and ſo what God is, what his wil is, what he requireth of vs, what we ought to doo, and what we ought to leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doon, what the dutie is of the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of God, what man is, and what kinde of one he is, what was his corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fall, and what was his ſetting
<pb facs="tcp:10066:49"/>
vp again, what is the ſaluation of man, in whom it conſiſteth and how they may obtain the ſame, who is Chriſte, what his redemption is, how far it extendeth.</p>
               <p>But there are infinite other ſuch like things, all which for ſo much as is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnto godlines and pietie, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Scripture dooth declare vnto vs and teach vs. Wherby we read in the Goſpel, that our Lord béeing ſo often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, how we ſhould be ſaued, what we ſhoulde doo, to enter in to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, which be the cheefeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God, what our dutie requireth wherwith God is moſte chéef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delighted: did alwaies after one ſorte make anſwere out of the holy Scripture, and ſent vs back to the holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>The rich glutton béeing in Hel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to come out from thence, and to teach and giue warning to his brethern,<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> he ſendeth him back to the Lawe and to the Prophets, that is to ſay, all the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, that deſire to be inſtructed touching the iudgements of God, and the ſtate of Soules in another world, he ſendeth them back, not vnto Ghoſtes or vnto ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits appéering in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſhape: but vnto the Scriptures. Wheruppon Paule
<pb facs="tcp:10066:50"/>
wrat vnto the Romaines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15</note>
                  <hi>VVhatſoeuer things haue been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: they were written for our lerning.</hi> Let vs therfore take the neceſſary rules of our religion out of the ſcriptures. And thoſe things, that are not taught in the Scriptures: let vs not think them to be either neceſſary or holeſome for vs.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, in true wiſdome it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit that wée bee taught nothing but that onely, which is true and good, and yet that wee ſhoulde vnderſtand alſo, what things are falſe, and ſo reſiſt the ſame.<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</note> It foloweth therfore in the woordꝭ of the Apoſtle, that héerin alſo the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is profitable, <hi>Pros elenchon,</hi> that is to ſay reproouing, and to the conuiction and confutation of falſhod, finally, to blaming, to accuſing, and to ſharp rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               <p>Therfore if any falſe Iugler, or crafty deceiuer bring in an opinion vntrue and vngodly,<note place="margin">Hereſies or confuted by the Scripture.</note> if hée corrupt the pure vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the woord, foorthwith the Scriptures miniſtreth holy arguments, with which the godly may confute ſuch a falſe deceiuer. And after that ſorte wée ſée, our Lord Ieſus to haue doon in the Goſpel, who, as often as either the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes
<pb facs="tcp:10066:50"/>
or els the Saduces were to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, with the Swoord of the Scripture, ſlew their falſe opinions and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therfore are they moſte fooliſh, who think that hereticks cannot be ouer come by the Scriptures onely, but that rather they are to be conuinced by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and decrées of councelles, or els by curſings.</p>
               <p>For we finde that <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle alſo in the acts of the Apoſtles, did with ſtand and ouercome bothe the rebellious Iewes, and alſo all the enemies of the Goſpel, with none other weapons, then of the Scriptures. And very well and in good time commeth héere to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance a noble ſentence of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines,</hi> which he vſeth againſte <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iminus</hi> the <hi>Arrian</hi> Heretick in his third Book and faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But now neither I ought to alledge the councel of Nice, neither thou the councel of A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riminu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as therby to obtaine the victory. And neither I nor thou to be bound to the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:10066:51"/>
of this man or that man. But by the authoritie of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, beeing witneſses not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to any, but common and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to vs bothe, let mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with matter, cauſe with cauſe, and reaſon with reaſon, contend togither.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſée therfore how Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> iudgement was, that the deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereſie of <hi>Arrius</hi> could be confuted by the Scriptures, and not by councels.</p>
               <p>But now at this day we haue the ſelf ſame Scriptures. What ſhould ſet ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but that we may with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſtrongly conuince all errors and hereſies, whatſoeuer, at what ſoeuer time they ſpring vp? For the Apoſtle had ſaid, that the Scripture is méer for confutation.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, if there be any thing corrupted in the Church (as many times the moſte excellent ordinances of God are peruerted either by the raſhnes,<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth.</note> or the ſuperſtition, or the fooliſhnes of man)
<pb facs="tcp:10066:51"/>
it is neceſſary to be amended. It folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth therfore in the Apoſtle, that héer alſo the Scripture is requiſit. <hi>Pros epano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoſin,</hi> that is to renew, and (as I may ſo ſay, to make ſtraight and amend.</p>
               <p>The holy hiſtories ſetteth foorth vnto vs in many and ſundry places, the vſe and example of that thing. For, as often as the ſinceritie and pureneſſe of Religion was defiled by the negligence, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ignorance and couetouſneſſe of the Rulers and the préeſts, and then by God were ſent Prophets and Kings, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the errors, that were generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: we read, that they did none other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe reforme and correct the Churche, then acording to the form and rule of the diuine Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The holy ſtory of <hi>Ioſaphat, Ezechias,</hi> and <hi>Ioſias,</hi> wel inough knowen. And alſo our Lord Ieſus, with holy Scripture correcteth the vices of his time corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting holy Matrimonie. He alſo purging the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> through the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetouſnes of the préeſts filthily conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in to a market place, dooth euen of his owne accorde bring foorth ſcriptures and ſayeth. <hi>It is written my houſe shalbe cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the houſe of prayer, but ye haue
<pb facs="tcp:10066:52"/>
made it a den for theeues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer it behooueth them, that are taught and reformed aright,<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture kepeth vs in order.</note> to be kept vnder the rule of diſcipline and good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, leſt at any time they doo vnchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and vnſhamefaſtly wax diſſolute and careleſſe. <hi>Paule</hi> therfore dooth ſhewe, that not ſomuche as in this behalfe, alſo any thing can be lacking in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For it is profitable (ſaith hée) <hi>Pros paideian,</hi> that is, vnto diſcipline and chaſtiſement. Zuor ziichtigung vnmeiſter ſcafft.</p>
               <p>For it miniſtreth the perfect rules of life and ſheweth ſharp chaſtiſements. In d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d from thence did <hi>Eſdras</hi> &amp; <hi>Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> fetch the right Diſcipline. From <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ence did the Apoſtle fetch his doctrine as often as he reprooued the Churches, that went a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ray into error, whome he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>adeth into the way again, and kéepeth them in order, with the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>What ſoeuer rules of life the Apoſtle preſcribeth to euery degree, euery kinde, and to euery age, the ſame he fetcheth out of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Finally, the holy Scripture dooth teache and inſtruct vs in all things, in which we haue any néed of teaching or
<pb facs="tcp:10066:52"/>
inſtruction. The ſame dooth reprooue, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buke, accuſe, drawe foorth, conuince, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute all kindes of errors, &amp; hereſies. The ſame correcteth, ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, reformeth, and finally keepeth vs vnder h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcipline, leſt we ſhould wax <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and run at ryot: and it is a moſte perfect Canon and a moſte ſure and infallible rule of holy life and true ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Therfore, why ſhould not the ſame ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffiſe in the Church, to gouern the men of this laſt age, and to deliuer them from all corruptions. Neither is there any cauſe, why we ſhoulde take vnto vs the rules, that is to ſay, the reuoltings and Apoſtacies, of the Munks. There is no cauſe, why we ſhould beg or borow theſe things neceſſary to ſaluation els where out of the ſtinking puddles of men, and out of the counterfet traditions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of men. The Fountain of liuing water is ſet foorth, and laid open vnto vs of God.</p>
               <p>But all thoſe partes of godly wiſdome and of chriſtian doctrine,<note place="margin">The drift of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and doctrin of God.</note> are directed to a certain and an onely end and mark, which the apoſtle addeth, and ſayeth. <hi>In rightuouſneſſe.</hi> But wee knowe that Chriſte is the righteouſnes of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.
<pb facs="tcp:10066:53"/>
To this end therfore all theſe things doo partain, namely, that Chriſte may liue in vs, and we in him, that he recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling vs to God, may take away our vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rightuouſneſſe, and ſo giue his rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe vnto vs, and that he may be our rightuouſneſſe before God the Father, through whome afterwarde wée might walk in rightuouſnes, during our whole life, with continuall repentance. For (as I haue ſhewed alredy) this is the only end and ſcope of the whole Scriptures.</p>
               <p>But neuertheleſſe, the purpoſe and meaning of the Apoſtles woords remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe as yet vnperfet. For the Apoſtle hath ſaid <hi>All Scripture giuen by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God is profitable to teach, to reprooue, to amend, to inſtruct in rightuouſnes.</hi> It foloweth that hée muſt make an end of the ſentence, and finiſh the matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the man of God may be made perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth perfect the true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of god</note> 
                  <hi>prepared vnto all good woorks.</hi> All the partes of this doctrin (ſaith hée) doo tend to this end, and doo woork this effect, that he, which wil be a faithful and perfect ſeruaunt of God, may want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therunto, but may obtain by the inſtruction of the Scriptures, to be made
<pb facs="tcp:10066:53"/>
perfect and prepared to euery good woork.</p>
               <p>Let vs note wel in theſe woords of the Apoſtle (yée reuerend Fathers and déer bretheren) how that vnto the Scripture is manifeſtly attributed a moſte abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perfection againſt the madnes and furies of all men, yea, againſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging blaſphemies of thoſe, that falſely affirm the ſame to be vnperfect and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and therfore méet to be patched vp with the rags of the traditions and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crées of the Church. <hi>That the man of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paule) may be made Perfet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perfet I ſay: <hi>Artios,</hi> whole, ſounde, abſolute in all pointes, and ſuch a one as lacketh nothing at all. What is it therfore that is néedful to be mended by theſe traditioners?</p>
               <p>Moreouer he addeth. <hi>Prepared vnto euery good woork.</hi> He ſaith not to one good woork or two, or a few good woorks: but to euery good woorke <hi>Exertiſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,</hi> prepared, perfited, ended, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trimmed vp, Vſgebutzt, made ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and finiſhed. Nothing therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for the Munks and Balles Traditioners, that ſhould by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions be added now at the length af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter certain hundred yéeres, to make the
<pb facs="tcp:10066:54"/>
matter perfet. The holy Scripture is moſte abſolute, moſte fully teaching all thoſe things that belong to the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of godly life and ſaluation. And the ſame is able throughly to faſhion or inſtruct, and make perfet the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy alſo.</note>Héerin alſo the holy Scripture dooth far ſurmount all Philoſophy, and all Philoſophers them ſelues, muche more the papiſticall Sophiſters, or traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Ball. Very triuily and very truely ſpake <hi>Firmianus Lactantius</hi> that Chriſtian <hi>Cicero,</hi> concerning falſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in his third Booke of inſtitutions, the xxvi. chapter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Onely the heauenly doctrine</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the which alone is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, bringeth to paſse thoſe things, which the Philoſophers were neuer able to doo. The commaundements of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſincere and pure, of how great force they are in the harts of men, dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:10066:54"/>
dooth shewe it. Bring me a man inclined to anger, il tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, vnruly, and rash, with a few of Gods words I wil make him as quiet as a lamb. Bring me a couetous perſon, a gree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy ſcraper and a nigard, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth wil I make him liberall. Bring me one that is feareful of death and of pain, ſtraight way he wil deſpiſe hothe Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes and fire, and daungers, yea, &amp; the torments of the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen bul. Bring me him that is a lecherer, and adulterer, a ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and a royater, hencefoorth shall thou ſee him ſober, chaſte, and continent. Bring me a cruel perſon, and one that thirſteth
<pb facs="tcp:10066:55"/>
after blood, ſoon shall that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bee chaunged into clemency and mercy. Bring me an vniuſt man, vnwiſe and ſinful, he shall be ſtraightway iuſt, wiſe, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and harmleſse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So great is the might of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome, that beeing powred into the hart of man: it wil at once euen with one push, expell and driue out foolishnes the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all ſin. Hath euer yet hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therto any of the Philoſophers performed theſe things? or if he were willing, were he able to doo it? Who, when they haue ſpent their whole time in the ſtudie of Philoſophy, yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſse are not able (if nature
<pb facs="tcp:10066:55"/>
do a litle withſtand it) to make them ſelues or any others the better therwith. Their wiſdom therfore (how much ſoeuer it can doo) yet dooth it not roote out vices but hide them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But a fewe of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements doo ſo throughly and wholly chaunge a manne, and by garnishing the olde, doo ſo make him newe, that thou canſt not knowe him to bee the ſame man he was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe very trim ſayings of <hi>Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius</hi> doo very much make to the praiſe of our holy Scriptures, or of the woord of God. The which woord in déed excelleth infinitly the wiſdome of the world, be it neuer ſo abſolute and perfet. So that this choſen &amp; ſpeciall Apoſtle of Chriſte, with very good cauſe would haue all the faithful, in all things to haue reſpect on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:10066:56"/>
to the woord of God, and to cleue faſt vnto the ſame euen to the very laſt breth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Concluſion</note>Moreouer now it ſhould remain for me, to gather thoſe things in to a ſhort ſumme, whiche I haue hitherto expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſomewhat at large, and to ſtir vp your mindes to a moſte feruent ſtudy and looue of the holy Scriptures, that bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtructed and prepared: yée might be the better able to kéep the flock com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your charge, from thoſe perils of theſe our daies, that be the laſt and therfore moſte corrupt, moſte miſerable, and ful of all calamities. But, ſéeing that through the ſinguler grace giuen vnto you from the Lord, ye be otherwiſe vigilant and watchfull, and doo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and féele alſo, to how greate and what kinde of daungers we are layde o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen and oppreſſed with all, whiche can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any way but onely by feruent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto God, and ſincere and diligent doctrine taken out of the Scriptures, be put back, driuen away, or be made vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hurtful to the godly. I wil now conclude with the holy and vehement woords of the bleſſed Apoſtle which he Ioyneth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly to thoſe which I haue all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:10066:56"/>
reherſed and expounded.</p>
               <p>He ſpeaking to euery one of vs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>I beſeech thee therfore before God and before our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, who shall iudge the quick and the dead at his appeering in his kingdom, preach the woord, be feruent in ſeaſon &amp; out of ſeaſon, reprooue, rebuke, exhorte with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the time wil come, when they will not ſuffer holeſome doctrine, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theire owne luſts shall they (whoſe eares itch) get them an heap of Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and shall turn their eare from the trueth vnto fables. But watch thou in all things, and ſuffer aduerſitie, and doo the woorks of an Euangeliſt, fulfill thine office to the vttermoſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, becauſe euery good gift, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perfect gift commeth from aboue, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from the Father of light: (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our humble petitions vnto him) let vs aſke of him thoſe things, whiche are neceſſary to the performing of this buſineſſe, waighty indéede and hard. And let vs pray <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
